<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Syr Bevis of Hampton</title>
            <title>Beuve de Hanstone.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 168KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09631</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847192</idno>
  <idno type="VID">12215</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240949422</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 1990</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S111932</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99847192e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09631)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12215)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 173:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Syr Bevis of Hampton</title>
                  <title>Beuve de Hanstone.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[72] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas East dwelling in Aldersgate streete,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1585]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Based on the twelfth-century Anglo-Norman chanson de geste "Beuve de Hanstone".</note>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>The couplets are printed as long lines--STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-I⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12215:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12215:1"/>
            <p>SYR BEVIS OF Hampton.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>Printed by Thomas East dwelling in Aldersgate streete.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:12215:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12215:2"/>
            <head>¶ THE HISTORIE OF Beuis of Hampton.</head>
            <l>LYsten Lordings and hold you still, of doubty men tell you I will,</l>
            <l>That haue ben in many a stoure, &amp; held vp England in great honor,</l>
            <l>That before this time hath bene, by a knight it is that I meane,</l>
            <l>sir <hi>Beuis</hi> of <hi>Hamtō</hi> y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> knight hight, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> neuer was proued a coward in fight.</l>
            <l>And by his father that hight sir <hi>Guy,</hi> a goodly knight and full hardy,</l>
            <l>And how sir Guy betrayed was, through his wife, alas, alas,</l>
            <l>That time was Guy of great renown, Earle he was of South-hampton,</l>
            <l>In Christendome farre and néere, of doughtines was not his peere.</l>
            <l>None was so hardy nor so strong, he loued the right and not the wrong,</l>
            <l>While sir <hi>Guy</hi> was yong &amp; light, known he was for a doughty knight,</l>
            <l>In euery land he rode and yede, for to winne him price and méed,</l>
            <l>In fraunce, in flanders &amp; in Almain, in Brabant, in Cicele &amp; in Britain.</l>
            <l>In Denmark, Gallice &amp; in Gascoyne, in Hungarie, Calabre &amp; Burgon,</l>
            <l>In Pole, in Normandy and Mayn, in Turky, Nabrant and in Spayn,</l>
            <l>In Eastland, Norway &amp; in Picardie, in Scotland, Wales &amp; in Lumbardy</l>
            <l>In christendom &amp; also in hethines, ful wel is known sir Guyes worthines</l>
            <l>In all the lands of Christentie, was none found so good as hée,</l>
            <l>While he was yong and iolife, would sir Guy wed no wife,</l>
            <l>But when that he was olde, he waxed féeble, croked and cold,</l>
            <l>Than toke he his leaue of Chiualrie, and dwelled in England certainly.</l>
            <l>In that time king Edgar anon, sent after Sir <hi>Guy</hi> full soone,</l>
            <l>For sir <hi>Guy</hi> was true and wise, and known for a knight of prise,</l>
            <l>He made him high steward of his land, &amp; whatsoeuer he said it shuld stād,</l>
            <l>He kéept well England in his daies, and set peace and stable lawes.</l>
            <l>That no man was so hardy, to doo an other villany,</l>
            <l>Vpon a day thought sir <hi>Guy,</hi> that he would wed some faire Lady,</l>
            <l>And haue betwéene thē some Children fair, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> of his land might be heir</l>
            <l>The king of Scotland in that tide, had a daughter of much pride.</l>
            <l>The Emperoures brother of Almayn, loued that lady as men sain,</l>
            <l>And so did <hi>Guy</hi> God him saue, and of her Father he did her craue,</l>
            <l>The king of Scotland for thy, gaue his daughter vnto sir <hi>Guy,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Against y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> wil of his daughter bright, she had leuer haue had y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> other knight</l>
            <l>For hée was yong and bolde, but sir <hi>Guy</hi> was waxen olde,</l>
            <l>Alas that euer hée her to him chose, his owne lyfe for to lose,</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:12215:3"/>
            <l>Sir <hi>Guy</hi> wedded that Lady frée, &amp; brought her hom to his country,</l>
            <l>So long to bed he her ladde, that a manchild together they had.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Beuis</hi> they called that childe bold, hée was no more then seuen yéere olde,</l>
            <l>When that his father he was slain, with sir <hi>Murdure</hi> of Almain,</l>
            <l>That Lady bethought her vpon a day, vnto her selfe gan shée say,</l>
            <l>My lord is olde &amp; may not worch, all day he bideth in the Church.</l>
            <l>What for brusing and what for age, he loueth not with me to rage,</l>
            <l>But had I taken a yong knight, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he had not béene brused in fight,</l>
            <l>He wuld loue mée both day &amp; night, &amp; make mée all y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mirth hée might,</l>
            <l>Truly it shalbe thus no while, I shall let slay him with some guile.</l>
            <l>After the messenger the Lady send, that before had béene her friend,</l>
            <l>She said thou shalt on my message, thy selfe alone without any page,</l>
            <l>So that thou kéepe my counsail, I shall quite well thy trauail,</l>
            <l>Madame he said holde you still, for I will do after your will.</l>
            <l>The Lady was then glad and fain, goe thou she said into Almain,</l>
            <l>And greet wel from mée sir <hi>Murdure,</hi> brother to the Emperour,</l>
            <l>And bid him in the first day, of the month of May,</l>
            <l>That he in the Forest bée, well armed with his meynye.</l>
            <l>Bid him that it be not leued, but that my Lord be there hedded,</l>
            <l>And send it mée for a present, my Lord shall naked to him be sent,</l>
            <l>If he me loue that shall I sée, goe forth and gréet him thus by mée,</l>
            <l>The Messenger to the Water yéede, alas the winde was all for speed.</l>
            <l>Into Almain he was brought, to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Court he went he forgot it nought,</l>
            <l>And asked soone of one an other, til he came to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Emperours Brother,</l>
            <l>And tooke the letter into his hand, the Lord it read as he there found,</l>
            <l>Now truly may I well sée, how that Lady loueth mée.</l>
            <l>Gladder I am though I it say, then any tongue tell may,</l>
            <l>All her will I meane to do, gréet her well and say to her so,</l>
            <l>Haue héere a stéed for thy trauaile, with treasure charged without faile,</l>
            <l>And if it stand in main and might, I my selfe shall make thée a knight,</l>
            <l>The messenger thanked him then, and to England hée is gone,</l>
            <l>To Hampton he came so in feare, of his enemies that wer there,</l>
            <l>And said my Lady God thée see, well sir <hi>Murdure</hi> gréeteth thée,</l>
            <l>Glad he is of thy message, full well he hath quit my voyage.</l>
            <l>And certainely he will be prest, with a great hoast in your Forrest</l>
            <l>Thy Lord to assail with main, and might, thy loue to winne lady bright,</l>
            <l>When the messenger had all said, the Lady held her well apayd,</l>
            <l>In the first day of May, the Lady fayned her sicke and lay.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:12215:3"/>
            <l>She made a man her Lord to call, and saide an euill did her befall,</l>
            <l>The Earle for her had sorow &amp; thought, &amp; asked her if she would ought,</l>
            <l>Sir shée said might I it get, of a wilde Bore I faine would eat,</l>
            <l>Dame he said and loue mine, where mighe I finde the wild swine.</l>
            <l>That might once glad thée, sir in your Forrest bréedeth hée,</l>
            <l>Dame he said make good solace, for to that Forrest I will goe chace,</l>
            <l>And shée said with treason then, blessed be thou of all men,</l>
            <l>The Earle a courser gan bestride, his sword he hanged by his side.</l>
            <l>There might no man with him rin, he was the formost man therein.</l>
            <l>Alas that he had béene ware, of his enemies that were there,</l>
            <l>
               <figure/>
            </l>
            <pb facs="tcp:12215:4"/>
            <l>But when he came to the Forrest, and in chase after the beast,</l>
            <l>Him thought he heard sir <hi>Murdure,</hi> cry aloud sir <hi>Guy</hi> thou traytour.</l>
            <l>And priked out before the hoast, for pomping pride to make great boast,</l>
            <l>And to sir <hi>Guy</hi> gan he say, yeald thée traytour for by my faye,</l>
            <l>Thou and thy sonne both dead shalbe, for the loue of thy Lady frée,</l>
            <l>For I her loued or thou her knew, if thou her haue it shall thée rew.</l>
            <l>Sir Guy him answered with reason, and said alas héere is treason,</l>
            <l>Yet will I so God mée mend, héere in my right mée defend,</l>
            <l>Either then gan other defie, then spurred his stéede good sir Guy,</l>
            <l>And smote sir Murdure with a spear, out of his saddle he gan him bear.</l>
            <l>Traitour he said ye and coward vnbolde, wéenest thou though I be olde,</l>
            <l>That I should of thée be ashamed, with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sir Guy his sword out wrested,</l>
            <l>And would haue slain that false knight, had not succour come ful right,</l>
            <l>Sir Murdures men hyed them so, against sir Guy they were full thro.</l>
            <l>Soothly sir Guy defēd him can, an hundreth hée slew with his hāds than,</l>
            <l>Had he béen well armed iwis, all the maistry had béen his.</l>
            <l>By than sir Murdure was horsed again, Sir Guyes horse they had slain,</l>
            <l>Alas his horse was slain that ylke stound, sir Guy was felled to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> groūd.</l>
            <l>For had his horse liued that tide, he had abated all their pride,</l>
            <l>When sir Guy was on foote without lesse, all they gan about him presse,</l>
            <l>You neuer heard of an olde man ere, that fought so long as he did ther,</l>
            <l>Then knéeled Guy to sir Murdure, and said mercy and succour.</l>
            <l>And sayd Murdure for thy gentry, thus cowardly let me not dye,</l>
            <l>But lend mée horse armour and shéeld, and let mée dye here in the féeld,</l>
            <l>And if with mée thou wilt doo so, I thée forgiue if thou mée slo,</l>
            <l>Then cryed they all in this wise, slay him that hee neuer rise.</l>
            <l>With that sir Murdure to him yede, and soone smote of his head,</l>
            <l>To a knight hée tooke his hed in hand, goe he said and beare this sond,</l>
            <l>To the Countesse that is so bright, &amp; say I come to her boure this night,</l>
            <l>The knight went to that Lady gent, &amp; said Madame haue this present.</l>
            <l>My Lord thée sent it sir Murdure, this night he commeth vnto thy bour,</l>
            <l>This gift she said is lefe to mée, and thanked sir Murdure of his gentry,</l>
            <l>And say I am all at his will, Early and late loud and still,</l>
            <l>The messenger went his way, and tolde his Lord what she did say.</l>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:12215:4"/>
               <head>How Beauis keept sheepe vpon the down, &amp; how that he left his sheepe and went to his Fathers house and how he slew the Porter, with other things that he did there.<figure/>
               </head>
               <l>NOw will we of yong Beuis tel, how he was &amp; how him befell,</l>
               <l>Alas he said and all for séen, that I had not with my father béene,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:12215:5"/>
               <l>To haue hope him in that stoure, against that false théefe sir Murdure,</l>
               <l>To his mother he ran and said, why hast thou my Father betraid.</l>
               <l>I will be auenged on his bane, alas that euer thou were woman,</l>
               <l>And all whores for thy sake, to the deuill of hell I them betake,</l>
               <l>But an oth mother I do sweare, If euer I may armes beare,</l>
               <l>I shall be auenged with might &amp; mayn, on thē that haue my father slayn.</l>
               <l>His mother his words vnderstood, and gaue him a buffet on the hood,</l>
               <l>To the groūd he fel that was harme, his master tooke him vp by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> arme,</l>
               <l>Men call his master sir Sabere, that child to him was life and déere,</l>
               <l>For Sabere was sir Guyes brother, in Englād was none such an other.</l>
               <l>Home with the childe Sabere went, the Lady after him sent,</l>
               <l>Sabere she said for well or for woe, my sonne Beuis looke that thou slo,</l>
               <l>For I shall neuer glad bée, that day that I him sée,</l>
               <l>Sir Sabere was not well apayd, but graunted as the Lady said.</l>
               <l>Home he went with Lordes few, and for a while a Pig he slew,</l>
               <l>Beuis clothes that was so good, he sprinkled with pigges blood,</l>
               <l>Sir Sabere then all for drede, clothed the childe in a poore wéed,</l>
               <l>And said Beuis thou must kéepe, vpon the féeld all my shéepe.</l>
               <l>Till the spousage be brought to end, &amp; then will wée to Wales wend,</l>
               <l>There is an Erle sibbe to thée, thou shalt there dwell and with him be,</l>
               <l>When thou art bigge &amp; armes to bear, &amp; hast strength harnesse to wear,</l>
               <l>Thē maist thou claim thine heritage, &amp; auenge thy father be thou of age.</l>
               <l>Then shall I help thée for to fight, with dint of sword to win thy right,</l>
               <l>Therfore my shéepe sée thou forth driue, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> no man know thou art on liue,</l>
               <l>Foorth went Beuis with Sabers shéep, vnto the féeld &amp; sore gan wéep,</l>
               <l>When Beuis a high vpon a down, he looked vp to South-hamptoun.</l>
               <l>And as he beheld toward the Towre, trumpets he heard and Tabour,</l>
               <l>Harping there was &amp; much blisse, in the place y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> should haue béene his,</l>
               <l>Lord he said of mée thou art gouernor, was not I an erles son of honour,</l>
               <l>I will no longer dwell in this downe, I will home to Southhamptoun.</l>
               <l>And will now sée for thy, what Murdure doth with that Lady,</l>
               <l>He ran fast on his yate, till he came to sir Murdures gate,</l>
               <l>Porter he said take none ill, for into the hall on message I will,</l>
               <l>Fye rebauld said the Porter tho, whorson harlot home thou goe.</l>
               <l>Ther was neuer mā but he wer mad, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> on message wuld send such a lad,</l>
               <l>Whorson said Beuis if I be one, yet Harlot was I neuer none,</l>
               <l>Thou shalt neuer strange man despise, haue this hée said for thy seruise,</l>
               <l>Such a stroke he him graffe, that the braine claue to the staffe.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:12215:5"/>
               <l>
                  <figure/>
               </l>
               <l>Beuis into the Hall went, with ragged clothes and sléeues rent,</l>
               <l>All about hée gan beholde, to sir Murdure he spake wordes bolde,</l>
               <l>False théefe what doost thou héer, why hast thou slain my father déer,</l>
               <l>My mother it is that thou hast tane, wend foorth in the diuels name.</l>
               <l>And if thou dwell against my leue, I trust to God I shall thée gréene,</l>
               <l>Then said sir Murdure hould you still, thou canst no good but much ill,</l>
               <l>Beuis hit sir Murdure at that word, that be sowned at the bourd,</l>
               <l>An other stroke he strok sadly; with that the Lady began to cry.</l>
               <l>Then Beuis would no longer abide, for knights rose on euery side,</l>
               <l>For yong Beuis woe there was, they tooke him not but let him passe,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:12215:6"/>
               <l>Beuis went home I you hete, he met his maister amids the stréete,</l>
               <l>What now Beuis said Sabere, for Gods sake what doost thou heere.</l>
               <l>Beaten I haue my stepfather, and slain I haue his owne Porter,</l>
               <l>Then said Sabere thou art to blame, ther I get both harme and shame,</l>
               <l>But betide what may betide, once againe I will thée hide,</l>
               <l>Sabere him to chamber led, of the Countesse he was a drede.</l>
               <l>The Countesse would neuer blin, vntill she came to Saberes Inne,</l>
               <l>Sabere she said where is become, that vncouth lad that strong fellon,</l>
               <l>Dame he said he is dead, at your counsaile and at your read,</l>
               <l>loe his clothes are all blood, thou lyest said she as thou were wood.</l>
               <l>But thou me that lad take, thou shalt suffer for his sake,</l>
               <l>Beuis heard that she him threat, to her he lept with hart great,</l>
               <l>And said to her Dame, do my maister for me no shame,</l>
               <l>The Lady said thou art bolde, now to me thy life is solde,</l>
               <l>Sabere and an other knight, she called to her anon right,</l>
               <l>Him to them betooke she, and bad them cast him into the sea,</l>
               <l>And cast the boy amids the streame, &amp; Sabere though thou be his came,</l>
               <l>But if thou drown this glutton, thou shalt abyd for that treason.</l>
               <l>Gladly my Lady certes said he, the childe they led vnto the sea,</l>
               <l>they wuld not drowne him for ought, but an other thing they haue thought.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How Beauis was soulde vnto the Paynims and caryed ouer the Sea into Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meny, and was presented vnto King Ermine.
<pb facs="tcp:12215:6"/>
                  <figure/>
               </head>
               <l>THey found ships both more and lesse, of Panimes &amp; of heathenesse,</l>
               <l>they sold y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> child w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> much thought, &amp; to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> paynimes Beues they raught</l>
               <l>Beuis hart waxed colde, for he was to Paynims solde,</l>
               <l>But yet him lyst not to rage, ouer they made good voyage.</l>
               <l>their saile they draw y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> wind was good, they sayled foorth as they wer wod</l>
               <l>Till they came to the riuer, Into the lande of Armony,</l>
               <l>The king Ermine of that land, his wife was I vnderstand,</l>
               <l>He had a daughter faire and bright, Iosian that faire mayde hight.</l>
               <l>His visage was whyte as lilly flour, therein ranne the red coulour,</l>
               <l>With bright browes &amp; eyes shéene, with haire as gold were on y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> gréene,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:12215:7"/>
               <l>With comely nose and lippes swéet, with louely mouth and faire féet,</l>
               <l>With téeth white and euen sette, her handes were swéet as vyolet,</l>
               <l>With gentle body withouten lacke, well shapen both belly and backe</l>
               <l>With smal hands &amp; fingers long, nothing of hir was shapen wrong.</l>
               <l>Wherefore should I hir not deceiue, there was neuer one fairer on liue,</l>
               <l>The Marchants are to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> court gone, &amp; presented y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> king with Beuis anon</l>
               <l>Therfore y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> king was faine &amp; blith, &amp; thanked y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Marchāts an hūdred sith,</l>
               <l>By Mahound said the king I were gaye, would the child forsake his laye,</l>
               <l>For by Mahound that sitteth on hie, yet saw I neuer childe with eye</l>
               <l>That bare so much fairenesse, neither in length nor in brodenesse,</l>
               <l>Child he said thy name tell me, wher thou wert borne &amp; in what coūtry,</l>
               <l>Sir he said Beuis is my name, wher I was borne think I no shame.</l>
               <l>In England my mother bare me, at South-hampton vpon the sea,</l>
               <l>My father thereof was Earle a while, my mother let slay him by a guile,</l>
               <l>And hath me sold to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Paynimes, a wickeder woman may none be iwis,</l>
               <l>And I may liue certinly, I shall auenge my father sir Guy.</l>
               <l>The king of Armony sayd ful wel, of Guy of Hampton I haue heard tel,</l>
               <l>Many a Paynime and sarasine, he hath slaine with much paine,</l>
               <l>Beuis he said I haue no heir, but a daughter that is faire,</l>
               <l>And thou wilt thy Lord forsake, and to Apolin our God thée betake</l>
               <l>I shall giue her to be thy wife, and all my land after my life,</l>
               <l>Sir he said that will I nought, for all things that euer was wrought,</l>
               <l>Neither for gift that may be, nor for thy daughter that is so frée,</l>
               <l>I did my selfe great dishonour, if I should forsake my creatour.</l>
               <l>The king had him in no fiaunce, for he was stedfast in his creuence,</l>
               <l>The king said Beuis while y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> art swain, thou shalt be my chamberlaine,</l>
               <l>When thou art dubbed a knight, thou shalt beare my banner in fight,</l>
               <l>Beues aunswered milde and still, what ye me bid doe I will.</l>
               <l>Beuis was loued of squire &amp; knight, for he was courteus both day &amp; night</l>
               <l>Iosian gan Beuis for to loue, ouer all things that was aboue,</l>
               <l>when Beuis was xiiii. yeare olde, knight nor Squire was none so bolde,</l>
               <l>That against Beuis durst ride, ne with no weapon him to abide.</l>
               <l>The first déede withouten lesse, that Beuis did in Hathenesse,</l>
               <l>It befell vpon Christmas day, how it was I will you say,</l>
               <l>Beuis rode to fielde him to solace, and sixtie Sarasines alas,</l>
               <l>A Sarasin gan to Beuis say, Beuis he said what hight this day,</l>
               <l>Beuis aunswered ywis, I wote not what it is,</l>
               <l>For I was but seuen yéere olde, to the Hathens when I was solde,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:12215:7"/>
               <l>Therefore felow blame not me, if I wote not what day it be,</l>
               <l>The Sarasines said and lough, we can tell thée well inough,</l>
               <l>This day is Christmas day, that thy God as men say,</l>
               <l>This day thou shouldst thy God honour, with some Nobles as we do ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Beuis vnto a Sarasine said, of Christendome I haue a brayd,</l>
               <l>I wold I wer as wel armed in this place, as euer sir Guy my father was,</l>
               <l>
                  <figure/>
               </l>
               <l>For his loue y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> ware the crowne of thorne, &amp; on this holy day was borne,</l>
               <l>Would I iust with all the rout, then should men sée without doubt,</l>
               <l>Whether he wer stronger in heauen, or all y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Mahounds y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> you can name</l>
               <l>Herken fellowes said a Sarasine, how he dispiseth Appoline.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:12215:8"/>
               <l>Yet weneth this Christen hound, that he would bring vs to the ground:</l>
               <l>We wil no longer haue respite, who so doth best shal be séen now right.</l>
               <l>Turne thée Beuis, we thée defie, there is nought els but thou shalt die.</l>
               <l>All at once on him they swong, and gaue him wounds wide and long.</l>
               <l>Beuis had no weapon great nor small, wherewith he might defend him withal.</l>
               <l>Ther was no boot for him to pray, but let him do y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> best he may</l>
               <l>Beuis was light and quicke, and to a Sarasine he lept</l>
               <l>And with his fist he stroke fast, that his chéeke bone all to brast.</l>
               <l>A Sarasines sword he toke in hand, &amp; felled al y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> before him wuld stād.</l>
               <l>There men might sée much woe, when Beuis began to goe,</l>
               <l>To some he gaue such woundes, that they lay grinning like houndes.</l>
               <l>The Sarasines were wight &amp; slie, and assailed Beuis with great enuie</l>
               <l>About Beuis the Sarasines did leape, as they had bin a flocke of shéepe.</l>
               <l>Of some he gan the womes downe teare, that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> guts trailed here &amp; there.</l>
               <l>There was no Sarasine that he hit, but his body asunder he cut.</l>
               <l>Ther might none fly by no side, but Beuis made him to abide.</l>
               <l>And Beuis within a litle stound, the sixtie Sarasins brought to groūd.</l>
               <l>Great game had Beuis to sée then, the dead Sarasins to lie and grinne.</l>
               <l>Here is séene said Beuis in this stound, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> God is stronger then Mahoūd.</l>
               <l>The Sarasines stéedes homeward ran, without taking of any man.</l>
               <l>And Beuis homeward gan ride, with bloudy woundes on each side.</l>
               <l>He stabled vp his horse thoe, and to his chamber gan he goe.</l>
               <l>To the fresh earth he layd him flat, for to stench his woundes with that.</l>
               <l>Tydinges came to king Ermine, that in despight of his God Appoline</l>
               <l>How Beuis had slain his men sixtie, vnto the king great shame &amp; villany</l>
               <l>The king swore neuer to eate bread, if it were so till he were dead.</l>
               <l>When Iosian it heard she was ful woe, and to hir father gan she goe:</l>
               <l>And said you ought not to giue iudgement, till both parties be present.</l>
               <l>Beuis is so mild of moob, I wote he did no man but good.</l>
               <l>By Mahound and by Termagaunt, but if it were his defendaunt.</l>
               <l>When we haue heard both parties, then it is time to do iustice.</l>
               <l>Then said the king bring both to me, as Iosian saith so shall it be.</l>
               <l>Iosian called foorth two knightes, goe your waies, she said foorth rightes,</l>
               <l>To Beuis Chamber that is so frée, and bid him come &amp; speake with me.</l>
               <l>To y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> chamber they went as she thē bad, eather other by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> hand they lad</l>
               <l>When they came to the chamber dore, the one knight went in before.</l>
               <l>And said Beuis is it thy will, to come speake with Iosian thy fill.</l>
               <l>Beuis lookt vp with grim visage, fie he said on your message.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:12215:8"/>
               <l>I will not once stirre off this ground, to speake with an heathen hound.</l>
               <l>Vnchristened houndes I read you flée, or I your hart blood shal sée.</l>
               <l>The knightes hyed them fast away, and vnto Iosian gan they say,</l>
               <l>Lady, Beuis called thée hound, thrise within a litle stound:</l>
               <l>We would not oft wend to him for all the cittie, he looketh so grimme.</l>
               <l>Yes said Iosian, come with me, and certaine I shall your warrant bée.</l>
               <l>With the maide foorth went they, to the chamber where <hi>Beuis</hi> lay:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Beuis</hi> looked vp anone, and Iosian in her armes twaine</l>
               <l>Tooke <hi>Beuis</hi> and kissed him swéete, his mallice she said she would wéet.</l>
               <l>She sayd, <hi>Beuis</hi> lemman thyne ore, thou art hurt wondrous sore.</l>
               <l>There is not in all Paynins land, better salue I vnderstand,</l>
               <l>Than I haue brought this stound, for to heale therewith thy wound,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Beuis</hi> rose vp at her bidding, and went foorth before the king.</l>
               <l>On <hi>Beuis</hi> was told there that tide, thirtie woundes long and wide</l>
               <l>King Ermine framed the truth and heard, how <hi>Beuis</hi> &amp; the <hi>Sarasins farde</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He had such ruth and pitie, that the teares ran down plentie.</l>
               <l>He sayd, daughter Iosian, Heale <hi>Beuis</hi> woundes if thou can,</l>
               <l>I would not as I vnderstand, lose his life for all my land.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iosian</hi> gan <hi>Beuis</hi> to chāber lead, to stop the wounds they should not bléed.</l>
               <l>With salues &amp; drinks she healed thē soft, &amp; euer among she kissed him oft.</l>
               <l>So within a litle stound, Beuis was whole and sound.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Beuis in a morning rose and went to the Forest, and slew the wilde Bore.
<pb facs="tcp:12215:9"/>
                  <figure/>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>AWyld bore was there about, all men of him had great doubt,</l>
                  <l>And all the men that he tooke, with his tusks he all to shooke,</l>
                  <l>The bore was much &amp; wondrous long, his head was great &amp; so was his tong</l>
                  <l>euery mā was grieued both knight &amp; king, for to come in his metīg,</l>
                  <l>Lord said Beuis vpon a day, whether it be as men doe say,</l>
                  <l>Certes my hart shall neuer be sore, till I haue foughten with the bore,</l>
                  <l>Beuis rose vp early vpon a day, and saddeled his good palfray,</l>
                  <l>Be tooke a swoord stiffe and strong, a good shield and a speare long,</l>
                  <l>And then he pricked ouer the fielde, Iosian saw and all behelde,</l>
                  <l>when Beuis came to the wood he shoke, his shield about his necke he tooke</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:9"/>
                  <l>His horse he tyed to a thorne, and began to blow with his horne:</l>
                  <l>All about the Forrest he sought, but the bore found he nought,</l>
                  <l>Till he came to the Deuils denne, there found he slaine many men:</l>
                  <l>That in the wood the bore slew, the bloud he dranke, and y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> flesh he gnew.</l>
                  <l>Rise he said thou foule beast, against me battaile sée thou heast.</l>
                  <l>When the bore of <hi>Beuis</hi> had an eye, he set his bristles all on hye.</l>
                  <l>And stared with his eies all hollow, as he would sir <hi>Beuis</hi> swallow.</l>
                  <l>Of thée said <hi>Beuis</hi> I haue meruaile, well I haue set my trauaile.</l>
                  <l>A speare to him <hi>Beuis</hi> did beare, in seuen péeces he burst it there.</l>
                  <l>All to weake that speare was wrought, for in the bore boote it nought.</l>
                  <l>His sword he drew him to were, but there might no dint him feare.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beuis</hi> thought at each dint, that he had smitten vpon a flint.</l>
                  <l>The bore smote at <hi>Beuis</hi> so hard, that he was néere faint coward.</l>
                  <l>Without rest fought they, till it was noone on the day.</l>
                  <l>Lord said <hi>Beuis</hi> helpe and mercie, I am so weary me thinke I die.</l>
                  <l>The bore was féeble and faint also, and from <hi>Beuis</hi> gan he goe.</l>
                  <l>Then sayd Beuis yet will not Iesu, that I should lose my vertue.</l>
                  <l>Betide sayd <hi>Beuis</hi> what may betide, the one of vs shall death abide.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beuis</hi> met the bore in the plaine, the bore saw that he turned agayne.</l>
                  <l>As he came gaping all to wonder, the ouer grone he smote asunder.</l>
                  <l>In at the mouth the bore he bare, and cloue his hart asunder there.</l>
                  <l>And with his sword all in hast, the bores head he off cast.</l>
                  <l>And on a tronche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n of a speare, the head he sticked for to beare.</l>
                  <l>That saw the fosters of that forrest, that <hi>Beuis</hi> had slaine that foule beast.</l>
                  <l>They sayd, wée haue great disdaine that he hath this bore slaine.</l>
                  <l>Goe we to him we shall him slay, and take the head from him away.</l>
                  <l>Then shall we haue all the honours, right as we were conquerours,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Beuis</hi> should from the forrest ride, they him beset on euery side.</l>
                  <l>The twelue fosters were armed each one, and <hi>Beuis</hi> was naked al alone.</l>
                  <l>Whē <hi>Beuis</hi> wold hād on his sword lay, the scaberd he found y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sword was away.</l>
                  <l>For he had left his sword thore, where he slew the wilde bore.</l>
                  <l>Then had he nought to weare, but the troncheon of a speare.</l>
                  <l>The Fosters smote he downe, with the stroke of a troncheowne.</l>
                  <l>Nine Fosters he slew at dintes thrée, and other thrée away gan flée.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beuis</hi> went with the head away: all saw Iosian where she lay.</l>
                  <l>Such loue on him she cast, that neuer failed, but euer did last.</l>
                  <l>The head of that wilde swine, <hi>Beuis</hi> presented king Exmine.</l>
                  <l>Then at the first rose <hi>Beuis</hi> price, that was both curteous and wise.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:10"/>
                  <l>SOne after not long during, came a messenger to Ermine king,</l>
                  <l>From king Bradmound of Damas, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> swore by Mahound &amp; Golyas,</l>
                  <l>But if king Ermine bleue, send Iosian to be his wife.</l>
                  <l>In many wayes he would him noy, and all his land robbe and distroy.</l>
                  <l>And said in the first day of Maye, He should come and hold his day.</l>
                  <l>And take away his daughter then, and all his landes destroy and bren.</l>
                  <l>King Ermine he was wood &amp; wroth, &amp; sent after Erles &amp; Barons both,</l>
                  <l>And told them without faile, that king Bradmound bad them battaile.</l>
                  <l>A word spake Iosian the bright, by Mahound sir were Beuis a knight,</l>
                  <l>He would succour you right well, my selfe saw where he did fell</l>
                  <l>Nine Fosters at dintes thrée, and other thrée away gan flée.</l>
                  <l>Yet had he nought to weare, but the truncheon of a speare.</l>
                  <l>Therfore sayd the king shall we not let, but Beuis shall to vs be fet.</l>
                  <l>And then he dubbed sir Beuis a knight, &amp; made him harnes for to fight.</l>
                  <l>Full well they gan for him puruay, with a great hoast against that day.</l>
                  <l>Beuis said the king, helpe at this néed, for all my men thou shalt lead.</l>
                  <l>Arme thée right &amp; take thy shield, for king Bradmound bideth in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> field.</l>
                  <l>Beuis did on he act owne, that had worthied many a towne.</l>
                  <l>An hauberk Iosiā to him brought, a better ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>berk was neuer wrought.</l>
                  <l>A helmet she gaue him good and faire, there might nothing it appaire.</l>
                  <l>Then to him that faire maid gaue, Morglay a sword both fine and braue.</l>
                  <l>There was no better vnder the Sun, many a land therewith was won.</l>
                  <l>Iosian gaue to him such a stéed, the best that euer on ground yéede.</l>
                  <l>Full well I can his name you tell, men called this stéed Arundell.</l>
                  <l>No horse in the world was so strong, that might him follow a furlong.</l>
                  <l>When Beuis in his saddle did light Iosian smiled that was so bright.</l>
                  <l>Beuis did his horne then blow, for that his hoast might him know.</l>
                  <l>Beuis had with him I vnderstand, of bold Barons twenty thousand.</l>
                  <l>And yet king Bradmound their foe, had thrise as many men and moe.</l>
                  <l>When Beuis came into the field, king B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>admound stood and all beheld.</l>
                  <l>A loude laughter laughed he then, when he saw ther was no more men.</l>
                  <l>Either of the hoasts gan other defie, they shot arrowes on either partie.</l>
                  <l>With bowes and alblasters of vice, they slew fast on either parties.</l>
                  <l>And when they were thus in fighting, there was earnest and no gaming</l>
                  <l>King Bradmounds banner bare Radison, he was as strong as any you.</l>
                  <l>Beuis at him had great enuie either of them did the other defie.</l>
                  <l>They smote their stéeds w<seg rend="sup">c</seg> spurs of gold, Arundel ran right as they wald</l>
                  <l>Both y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> parties stood &amp; beheld, how either hit other in midst of their shield.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:10"/>
                  <l>Radisons speare all to brast, Beuis speare held and smot fast.</l>
                  <l>That through the shield and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>on, he bare the great king Radison,</l>
                  <l>The speare burst and he fel downe, in his breast he felt the troncheon.</l>
                  <l>Then king Bradmound was abashed, for in Radison all they trusted.</l>
                  <l>For they thought he was so maine, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> no man might stand him againe.</l>
                  <l>About sir <hi>Beuis</hi> they came redely, to auenge his death on the other party.</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Beuis</hi> had game, &amp; thought ful good, to bath Morglay in their bloud.</l>
                  <l>Men might sée in that stound, an hundred Sarasines brought to ground.</l>
                  <l>A litle further he rode tho, and slew twice as many inoe.</l>
                  <l>The Sarasines that with <hi>Beuis</hi> were, helped him fast with their power.</l>
                  <l>Men might sée ouer all, heads trundle like a ball.</l>
                  <l>Many Sarasines might men méet, with guts trailing about their féete.</l>
                  <l>Some all headles gan flée, and some all shankles aboue the knée,</l>
                  <l>And some their heads off he sent, and some noseles away went.</l>
                  <l>And some fled with so great wounds, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> they lay grinning like to hounds.</l>
                  <l>A thousand stéedes men might sée then, with dead Sarasines away renne.</l>
                  <l>And all the sicke and whole, had bene before at <hi>Beuis</hi> dole.</l>
                  <l>Bradmound sée his men misfare, two of <hi>Beuis</hi> knightes he tooke there.</l>
                  <l>And led them foorth, and then he fled: <hi>Beuis</hi> saw that they were bested,</l>
                  <l>And sayd abyde thou olde wretch, art thou come Iosian to fetch.</l>
                  <l>Yéeld thy prisoners vnto mée, I will deliuer them from thée.</l>
                  <l>Such stroke he gaue Bradmound, that man and horse fell to the ground.</l>
                  <l>Mercy sayd Bradmond thyne ore, let me liue and smite me no more.</l>
                  <l>The Citie with castles &amp; towres, I shall thée giue with great honours.</l>
                  <l>Nay said <hi>Beuis</hi> I wil none of thyne, but become y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> kings mā of Ermine.</l>
                  <l>And doo homage and fealtie, for other wages there shall none bée.</l>
                  <l>Well said Bradmound I had leuer do so, then here to dye w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> pain, &amp; woe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beuis</hi> charged him in his lay, that he would neuer by night or by day,</l>
                  <l>Wayte king Ermine any treason, but be euer ready at his summon.</l>
                  <l>And hold him of his landes as chéefe, be thou loth or be thou léefe.</l>
                  <l>Beuis was Ermines atturney, to receiue homage on that day.</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Beuis</hi> had done he let him goe, alas why did he not him sloe.</l>
                  <l>For soone after as you may heare, he serued him in worse manere.</l>
                  <l>The knights y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he tooke frō Bradmoūd, <hi>Beuis</hi> led foorth with him y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> stoūd.</l>
                  <l>For great loue he would not blin, but both he led vnto his Inne.</l>
                  <l>And gaue them of meat &amp; drinke the best, and in his bed did bid them rest.</l>
                  <l>And when sir <hi>Beuis</hi> had done so, vnto the King he then did goe.</l>
                  <l>And said, sir K. make good visage, for K. Bradmoūd hath done thée homage.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:11"/>
                  <l>And holds thée for chéefe in field &amp; towne, &amp; wil be ready at thy somowns.</l>
                  <l>The king Ermine was glad and blithe, and blessed <hi>Beuis</hi> often sith:</l>
                  <l>And said faire daughter Iosian, I pray thée soone vnarme this man</l>
                  <l>Lead him to a chamber, Mahound him saue, for therein he may rest haue.</l>
                  <l>And serue him both of meat and drinke, of the best that you may thinke.</l>
                  <l>Then faire Iosian was right glad, and to her chamber him she led.</l>
                  <l>And Beuis was set soft on a bed, the bordes were layd and tables spred.</l>
                  <l>When shée had vnarmed <hi>Beuis,</hi> at a boord she set him ywis.</l>
                  <l>And made them well at ease and fine, with rich meat and noble wine.</l>
                  <l>When they had well eaten, and on a bed togither sitten.</l>
                  <l>Iosian that was so true, thought shée would her loue renne.</l>
                  <l>She sayd, Beuis I vow to thée, aboue all thinges I do loue thée.</l>
                  <l>And if thou loue mée not againe, I shall be dead through woe and paine.</l>
                  <l>Then said Beuis bée thou still, mée thinks thou speakest without skill.</l>
                  <l>Thou mayst haue all vnliche, the king Bradmound that is so riche.</l>
                  <l>In all the world is no man, neither King, Duke, or Soudan,</l>
                  <l>But they would haue thée to their Quéene, &amp; if they had thée once séene.</l>
                  <l>I am a knight of strange land, and haue no more then I in stand.</l>
                  <l>Mercy Beuis said Iosian, I had rather haue thée for my lemman,</l>
                  <l>Thy body in thy shirt naked, then all the good that Mahound maked.</l>
                  <l>Beuis shée sayd, tell mée thy thought: Beuis sat still and said nought</l>
                  <l>Shée fell downe and wept sore, saying thou saidst here before,</l>
                  <l>Ther is no king that mée hath séen, but that hée would haue mée to quéene.</l>
                  <l>And thou thinkst on mée great spight, wend thou out of my chāber right.</l>
                  <l>More comely it were thée like, for to hedge and make a dike,</l>
                  <l>Then now for to bée dubbed a knight, &amp; to dwell among maydens bright.</l>
                  <l>Goe churle, and euill mayst thou fare, Mahound giue thée sorrow &amp; care.</l>
                  <l>Damosell he sayd, I am no churle, my father was both knight and Erle,</l>
                  <l>To my countrey I will mée hye, neuer after thou shalt mée sée.</l>
                  <l>Thou gauest mée horse, take him héere, I kéepe not to bée in danger.</l>
                  <l>Beuis went foorth hée would not blinne, till hée came into his Inne.</l>
                  <l>Sore gréeued as hée were blamed, for Iosian had him so ashamed.</l>
                  <l>The two knights that Beuis loued, asked him who had him gréeued.</l>
                  <l>Beuis sayd neither good nor ill, but sat him downe and held him still.</l>
                  <l>When Beuis went Iosian fro, then did begin all the woe.</l>
                  <l>Then she called the Chamberlaine Boniface, and his helpe in that case.</l>
                  <l>To Beuis on message shée him send, and sayd shée would al things amēd,</l>
                  <l>All that shée did say truly, and pray him for to come to mée.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:11"/>
                  <l>Boniface his waye is gone, to Beuis Chamber is hée come.</l>
                  <l>And sayd that Iosian had him send, and that she would all amend.</l>
                  <l>And al that shée had sayd loud and still, so that you would come her till.</l>
                  <l>Beuis sayd why should I do so? shée bad mée wend her chamber fro.</l>
                  <l>A robe gaue Beuis to the messenger, with other wéedes faire and cléere,</l>
                  <l>Well furred of great valour, haue this hée said for thy labour:</l>
                  <l>And gréet well thy Lady from mée, and say I will her neuer sée.</l>
                  <l>Boniface thanked him then, and to Iosian went againe.</l>
                  <l>Hée sayd my Lady make good chéere, for Beuis will no more come héere.</l>
                  <l>Certes Madam yée did vnright, for to missay a noble knight.</l>
                  <l>For it was neuer a churles déed, to giue a messenger such a wéed.</l>
                  <l>If Beuis will not come to mée, I will not blin while I him sée.</l>
                  <l>befall me therfore well or woe, vnto his chamber wil I goe.</l>
                  <l>Iosian would no longer blin, till she came to Beuis Inne,</l>
                  <l>When Beuis heard her without, as he should sléepe he began to route.</l>
                  <l>Beuis shée sayd awhile awake, I am come peace to make.</l>
                  <l>Faire Damosell then said hée, let me alone, and goe from me.</l>
                  <l>I am weary of fighting ful sore, so will I for loue no more.</l>
                  <l>Mercy she said my lemman swéet, shée fell down and began to wéepe.</l>
                  <l>Forgiue me that I haue missayd, I wil that yée be well apayd.</l>
                  <l>My false gods I will forsake, and Christendome for thée to take.</l>
                  <l>On that couenant said Beuis than, I will thée loue faire Iosian.</l>
                  <l>He kissed her to accordement, and therefore was Beuis shent.</l>
                  <l>The two knights were ther that stound, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Beuis took from K. Bradmoūd.</l>
                  <l>They heard all their couenant, and went to the king in an instant.</l>
                  <l>And sayd, Beuis this same day, hath made Iosian forsake her lay.</l>
                  <l>And surely he will lye her bye, except ye séek some remedy.</l>
                  <l>And least that he be sent away, he will distroy all your lay.</l>
                  <l>It is true by All hallows, deliuer a théefe from the gallowes,</l>
                  <l>He shall thée waite to robbe or slo, so it fared by these knights two.</l>
                  <l>Beuis deliuered them from perill, and they requited him full ill.</l>
                  <l>Alas then sayd Ermine the king, sore I am grieued at this tyding.</l>
                  <l>Sithen that Beuis came me till, much he hath done at my will.</l>
                  <l>I would not for all Armeny, Sée any do Beuis villany.</l>
                  <l>but I would faine auenged be, so that the deed I might not see.</l>
                  <l>And then a Sarafine to him said, ther may be in parchment made,</l>
                  <l>A letter vnto king Bradmound, and bid that he be brought to ground.</l>
                  <l>As he is true knight to you sworne, and by beuis shal the letter be borne.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:12"/>
                  <l>And by Mahound I dare say, Beuis shal neuer goe quite away.</l>
                  <l>When this was brought vnto the ende, the king did after <hi>Beuis</hi> send.</l>
                  <l>And said thou shalt go foorth right, &amp; be true messenger as thou art knight.</l>
                  <l>And beare king Bradmoūd this letter, &amp; euermore thou shalt be y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> better.</l>
                  <l>Some other els should sure beare it, but it shal turn thée to great profit.</l>
                  <l>Sir, let me haue Arundell and good Morglay, I dare vndertake the way.</l>
                  <l>Be Bradmound neuer so wrath or wood, I shall make my partie good.</l>
                  <l>Wherfore said Ermin thenkest thou so? thou shalt but on my message go.</l>
                  <l>Take therefore an easie hackney, that may beare thée easily away.</l>
                  <l>It becommeth no messenger to leade, on message so vncomely such a stéed.</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Beuis</hi> thou shalt to me sweare, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> thou shalt truly my letters beare.</l>
                  <l>And if thou art true man liefe, vndoe not the print of my briefe.</l>
                  <l>Nay said Beuis on Christen Rood: he tooke his letter and foorth yode,</l>
                  <l>Vpon an ambling hackney, leauing at home Arundell and Morglay.</l>
                  <l>Iesu him comfort and rede, vpon him he beareth his owne déede.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>LEaue we now of Beuis here, and speake we of his eame Sabere.</l>
                  <l>After that Beuis was from him sold, his hart for him waxed cold.</l>
                  <l>He called to him his sonne Terrye, and bad him wend to espye.</l>
                  <l>To Sarasines land both farre and néere, if he might ought of <hi>Beuis</hi> heare.</l>
                  <l>Palmers wéed thou shalt weare, so maist thou better after him spere.</l>
                  <l>He gaue him treasure for to spend, when that is done God can more send.</l>
                  <l>Foorth then gan child Terrye fare, to Sarasines land till he came there.</l>
                  <l>In many a land he hath sought, but of Beuis he heard nought.</l>
                  <l>Till it befell vpon a day, as afterward I shall you say.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:12215:12"/>
               <head>How Beuis went on message to king Bradmound, and how hee fought in the Cittie of Damas against the Sarasines that made sacrifice to Idols, and how he tare them downe and cast them into the durt and afterward was taken and put in prison.<figure/>
               </head>
               <l>TVrne againe wher we were before, of <hi>Beuis</hi> of Hāpton to speake more.</l>
               <l>Beuis rode foorth and passed fast, toward the citie of Damas.</l>
               <l>He rode dayes and nights both, and rested not without othe,</l>
               <l>He rode as fast as he might ride, two or thrée morrowes tide.</l>
               <l>Then list he both to drinke and eate, as a weary man doth after heate.</l>
               <l>To sléepe he had lust the Romaines tels, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> might he get and nothing els.</l>
               <l>Beuis lay downe to sléepe a stound, and let his horse baite on the ground.</l>
               <l>When he awoke out of his sléepe, no longer he abode, but vp he did leape.</l>
               <l>He came to a Forest faire and brode, and thetherwardes as he rode,</l>
               <l>He saw a Palmer sit him néere, with bread and wine at his dinner.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:12215:13"/>
               <l>Baken curlewes had he three, though hee seemed poore to be.</l>
               <l>The Palmer saw beuis was a knight, he vailed his bōnet as it was right</l>
               <l>And said to him faire loue myne, is it your will to come and dine?</l>
               <l>For my will is so giuen to thee, therefore sir knight forgiue it mee.</l>
               <l>Thou shalt wish me ful euen, to a man that I can name,</l>
               <l>Beuis sayd to him agayne, hunger hath done me much payne.</l>
               <l>Beuis eat and dranke good plentie, while he would sit and therat be.</l>
               <l>Then to speake beuis Began, Palmer he sayd art thou a Christian?</l>
               <l>Where wert thou borne, tell to me, and what thou dost in this countrie?</l>
               <l>Then said the Palmer ye shal vnderstand, that I was borne in England.</l>
               <l>At Southhampton vpon the sea, and am come into this countrye,</l>
               <l>To séek after a child I plyght, Forsooth beuis he hight.</l>
               <l>I shall him séek till I him finde, though I him séek to the worlds end.</l>
               <l>To bring him to England, to helpe my father with his hand.</l>
               <l>Against his stepfather for to fight, to win his heritage and right.</l>
               <l>What hight thy father Palmer? sir men call him Saber.</l>
               <l>Sir he hath bin euer in strife, sith sir Guy of Hamptons life.</l>
               <l>I left him in an Ile full good, that is inclosed with the salt flood.</l>
               <l>And euery yeare a day certaine, he fighteth with sir Murdure of Almaine</l>
               <l>For to win his heritage, he doth for him great voyage.</l>
               <l>Tell me therefore if you can, wish me right vnto that man.</l>
               <l>Then said <hi>Beuis</hi> with milde cheare, <hi>Beuis</hi> haue I knowne this ten yeare.</l>
               <l>It is not thrée dayes at all, sithen we were both in one hall.</l>
               <l>Ther is no man by Gods ore, in Christendome that I loue more.</l>
               <l>We were fellowes for thy, he told me his father hight sir Guy.</l>
               <l>Sir said the Palmer that is he, for Gods loue let me him see.</l>
               <l>Nay sayd <hi>Beuis</hi> it may not be so, for on a message must I goe.</l>
               <l>but goe thou to England againe, helpe thy father with might and mayne.</l>
               <l>For when I haue my message done, I shall speake with <hi>Beuis</hi> ful soone.</l>
               <l>And tell him as I vnderstand, and make him to hye into England.</l>
               <l>Perchaunce <hi>Beuis</hi> is my frend, I shall with him to England wend.</l>
               <l>Sir sayd the Palmer in his language, to whom do ye ride on message.</l>
               <l>To king Bradmound sayd <hi>Beuis</hi> I wend, he is my foe and not my frend.</l>
               <l>Sayd the Palmer if thy will bée, wilt thou let me thy letter sée.</l>
               <l>Nay sayd Beuis so mote I goe, so thought I not my selfe to doe.</l>
               <l>It shall neuer vndone bée, till king Bradmound doth it see.</l>
               <l>They tooke their leaue and foorth gan goe, either kissed other of thē two.</l>
               <l>The Palmer went to England ward, and Beuis did ride on forward.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:12215:13"/>
               <l>Towardes the Citie of Damace, the which was a full faire place:</l>
               <l>There was K. Bradmounds pallace, was neuer none richer y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> story sayes.</l>
               <l>For both the windowes &amp; the walles, was painted w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> gold, towers &amp; hals.</l>
               <l>Pillers &amp; dores were al of brasse, windowes of lattin were set with glasse.</l>
               <l>It was so riche in many wise, that it was like to Paradice.</l>
               <l>About the place there was a dyke, for breadth and depth were few it like.</l>
               <l>Ouer the ditch a bridge there lay, that man and beast might passe way.</l>
               <l>Vnder the bridge were sixtie belles, right as the Romaines telles.</l>
               <l>That there might no man passe in, but all they rang with a ginne.</l>
               <l>At the bridge end there was a tower, painted with gold and asoure:</l>
               <l>Ritch it was for to behold, thereon stood an Eagle of gold:</l>
               <l>His eies were of precious stones, of great vertue for the nones.</l>
               <l>The stones were so ritch and bright, that all the place shone with light.</l>
               <l>When Beuis was néere vnto the citie, of that place meruailed he.</l>
               <l>For sithen Beuis borne was, saw he neuer such a place.</l>
               <l>When <hi>Beuis</hi> came the citie within, great mirth and noyse he saw begin.</l>
               <l>The Sarasines then should sacrafice, to their Maumets in this wise.</l>
               <l>And Beuis came néere for to sée, saying what deuill of hell doe yée?</l>
               <l>Why make you Mahound this present, and dispise God Omnipotent?</l>
               <l>I shall witte before I goe, what Mahound can say or doe.</l>
               <l>Beuis lept vnto Mahound, and tooke him right by the crowne,</l>
               <l>And cast him amidst the mire, and bad them take vp their syre.</l>
               <l>The Sarasines that by Beuis stood, for yre &amp; téene they were néere wood.</l>
               <l>They swore all he should abye, for he despysed their Mawmetry.</l>
               <l>There was no more for them to say, but all at once on him they lay.</l>
               <l>Beuis saw that, his sword he drew, and all that would abyde he slew.</l>
               <l>Then rose the crye in the citie, and Sarasines gathered great plentie.</l>
               <l>About sir Beuis they gathered, because Mahound he despysed.</l>
               <l>Beuis then did make a stoure, at each stroke he felled foure.</l>
               <l>With the Sarasines he fought so fast, that two hundred to ground he cast.</l>
               <l>Within a while men might méete, heads tumbling in the stréete.</l>
               <l>To the pallace they ranne flying, for to haue succoure of the king.</l>
               <l>And sayd, sir wee are sore noyed, for the citie is néere destroyed,</l>
               <l>Through a knight that hether is come, all our Gods he hath puld down,</l>
               <l>And troden them vnder his féete, in the mire amids the stréete.</l>
               <l>And all thy men he hath slayne, that euer did fight him againe.</l>
               <l>Sir king but we haue counsell of thée, he will destroy all the citie.</l>
               <l>King Bradmound sayd, by my God, be he a deuill, or be he wood,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:12215:14"/>
               <l>What is he I will goe sée, arme you right and come with me.</l>
               <l>Foorth they went all the rout, of the kinges Pallace without doubt.</l>
               <l>Right on the bridge y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Romaines sayes, they met him going to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> pallace.</l>
               <l>When Beuis saw y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> king with crowne, vpon his knées he knéeled downe.</l>
               <l>And gaue him vp the déed with his hand, &amp; sayd, Iesus that I vnderstand,</l>
               <l>That shaped al y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> world so round, now giue thée sorrow king Bradmoūd.</l>
               <l>But Mahound and Apolyne, and Termagaunt which be Gods thyne:</l>
               <l>Let them giue thée now their blessing, that short life, and euill ending.</l>
               <l>Well thée gréeteth king Ermine, and sendeth thée a letter in parchmine.</l>
               <l>And biddeth thée his bidding doe, as thou art sworne him vnto.</l>
               <l>The king of Beuis receiued the déed, and gaue it to a clearke to reade.</l>
               <l>The letter bad he should him slo, and that he should not goe him fro:</l>
               <l>For certis if he passe away, he will destroy all your lay.</l>
               <l>When king Bradmoūd heard of this, he made therfore great ioy &amp; blisse.</l>
               <l>He said, <hi>Beuis</hi> welcom to court w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> shame, we shall teach thée a new game.</l>
               <l>Thou art he that made me thrall, not onely me but my men all.</l>
               <l>Thou slewest &amp; broughtest my men to ground, xx. M. within a litle stoūd.</l>
               <l>And hast in despyte of Mahound, slayne my men in this stound.</l>
               <l>But euer blessed may Mahound be, that sent thée hether vnto me.</l>
               <l>For I will be auenged soone, of all the sorrow thou hast me done.</l>
               <l>But wite me not Beuis verament, but blame him that thée hether sent.</l>
               <l>Some said he should be slayne, and some he should be quicke flayne.</l>
               <l>Some said, draw him through the citie, and some said hang him on a trée.</l>
               <l>Beuis he stood still and heard, of all the treason how it farde.</l>
               <l>And said sir king it is no réede, to iudge me to a dogs déede.</l>
               <l>A knight I am as well as you, therefore take your counsaile now,</l>
               <l>And graunt me armour and stéede, sword and speare good at néede.</l>
               <l>Sure helme and stalworth shield, and bring me safe into the field.</l>
               <l>And arme your men lesse and more, sixtie thousand if they wore.</l>
               <l>And let me die in battayle right, as is the manner of a knight.</l>
               <l>Then the Sarasines cryed all, and to the king gan they call,</l>
               <l>And sayd he shall thy men downe fold, if thou graunt him battaile bold.</l>
               <l>Graunt him prison through our read, let him be there till he be dead.</l>
               <l>For in your prison be Dragons two, and other wormes many moe.</l>
               <l>And were he in your prison brought, vnto noone liueth he nought.</l>
               <l>Bring him thether they all said then, and not in field among your men.</l>
               <l>Then spake king Bradmound, bring him downe vnto the ground:</l>
               <l>For he shall dye with much sorrow, all Christendom shal not him borow.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:12215:14"/>
               <l>About Beuis gan they driue, as Bées do about an hiue.</l>
               <l>When Beuis saw none other rest, then he began to doe his best.</l>
               <l>With his sword he stood at defence, against them all in their presence.</l>
               <l>Sir Beuis fought that it was wonder, till his sword burst in sunder.</l>
               <l>Alas sayd Beuis and well away, now I want good Morglay.</l>
               <l>But neuerthelesse Beuis, brought to ground with his fistes:</l>
               <l>Sixtie Sarasines to ground he cast, after that his sword did brast.</l>
               <l>But euer they gathered moe and moe, and tooke Beuis with much woe.</l>
               <l>And bound together his handes so fast, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> al his fingers on blood out brast.</l>
               <l>They led him straight into the hall, and set him downe in a knights stall.</l>
               <l>A knight him fed with meat &amp; drinke, whatsoeuer he would after thinke.</l>
               <l>The king bad Beuis eat fast, for this he sayd shall be thy last.</l>
               <l>An hundreth Sarasines stood then, about Beuis with swordes drawne.</l>
               <l>In chaunce if his handes out brast, then should he make them all agast.</l>
               <l>Whē <hi>Beuis</hi> had eatē &amp; made him glad, into y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> prison they made him be lad.</l>
               <l>When he was at the ground, Beuis handes they vnbound.</l>
               <l>For they were sure and fast, that he should not make them agast.</l>
               <l>In the prison when he came downe, there he found a short trunchone.</l>
               <l>In his handes the same he tooke, and saued his life so sayth the booke.</l>
               <l>A water through the prison ranne, and bare the filth from the man.</l>
               <l>He had not bene there but a whyle, not the mountenance of a mile.</l>
               <l>But two Dragons of much might, against sir Beuis came to fight.</l>
               <l>Fast fought both he and they, all the night and all the day.</l>
               <l>The two Dragons neuer stayde, till they had Beuis weary made.</l>
               <l>But by the other day at noone, these two Dragons were fordone.</l>
               <l>His staffe was broken all away, but litle in his hand did stay.</l>
               <l>When these two Dragons were dead, then could Beuis no better read.</l>
               <l>But thanked Iesu that all shall winne, of all the care that he was in.</l>
               <l>Seuen winters he was thore, meate he had euermore.</l>
               <l>But once a day without lesse, of Wheat branne he had a messe.</l>
               <l>For to length withall his life, in pouertie and in great strife.</l>
               <l>Bread of corne eate he none, but of water he had great wone.</l>
               <l>Rats and Mice and such small chere, was his meat that seauen yeare.</l>
               <l>Thus is Beuis in prison ground, God bring him out whole and sound.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Iosian demaunded her father for sir Beuis, and of the sorrow that shee made.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:12215:15"/>
               <l>SPeake we of Iosian that mayd, vnto her father how she sayd.</l>
               <l>Sir Beuis she sayd where is he, ful long me thinketh til I him sée.</l>
               <l>Daughter he sayd I vnderstand, that he is gone into England.</l>
               <l>And liueth on his heritage, he hath a wife of great parentage.</l>
               <l>A kinges daughter wedded hath he, a marchant ywis told it mée.</l>
               <l>Then was Iosian full woe, and to her chamber gan she goe.</l>
               <l>And wept sore for sir Beuis, and thought some treason here is.</l>
               <l>There is no man can tell the sorrow, that she made both euen &amp; morow.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How King Iour wedded faire Iosian.<figure/>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:15"/>
                  <l>OF Mambrant the king called Iour, a ritch king &amp; of great treasure:</l>
                  <l>Is come fayre I sian to wedde, and of her father he him spedde.</l>
                  <l>That graunted her to his wife, and his land after his life.</l>
                  <l>Whē Iosian heard she should be Quéene, against her wil it was I wéene.</l>
                  <l>She had leuer withouten lesse, to haue bene sir Beuis countesse.</l>
                  <l>Neuerthelesse, sith it is so, against her father she durst not doe.</l>
                  <l>Euer she said, good sir Beuis, hinde knight of Southhampton is.</l>
                  <l>Haddest thou neuer me forsake, but some treason did it make.</l>
                  <l>I shall neuer so vntrue be, as thou art Beuis vnto me.</l>
                  <l>I shall goe now and make me a writte, through a clarke wise of witte.</l>
                  <l>That no man shall haue grace, while these letters are in place.</l>
                  <l>Against my will to lye me by, nor do me shame nor villany.</l>
                  <l>She caused the letters to be wrought, on the maner as she had thought.</l>
                  <l>And put it about her necke, so that no man should her checke.</l>
                  <l>When it was to the time sped, that king Iour should her wedde:</l>
                  <l>He sent for many noble men, or the Soudan of Babilon then.</l>
                  <l>And for the Soudan of Persy, it is no time their names to discrye.</l>
                  <l>And prayed them both with him to be, when he should wed that lady frée</l>
                  <l>When this feast should beginne, euery knight went to his Inne.</l>
                  <l>When the feast was all done, king Iour would home come.</l>
                  <l>With Iosian the lady bright, that euer was true both day and night.</l>
                  <l>Iosian was brought to him there, with much thought and much care.</l>
                  <l>King Ermine tooke Arundell, and sadled him goodly and well.</l>
                  <l>And tooke with him good Morglay, and to king Iour gan he say.</l>
                  <l>Haue here I giue thee this steed, stalworth and good at neede.</l>
                  <l>Haue here Morglay of steele broune, both they were Beuis of Hampton.</l>
                  <l>King Iour thanked him then, and pricked foorth before his men.</l>
                  <l>They were not fully at Mambrant, but the king said by Termagant,</l>
                  <l>That he would into the citie ride, on Arundell before his bride.</l>
                  <l>On Arundell when he was brought, Arundell had in his thought,</l>
                  <l>That it was not sir Beuis, that on his backe did sitte ywis.</l>
                  <l>He leaped ouer ditch and thorne, ouer bryer and ouer corne,</l>
                  <l>Would he neuer blinne running, till he had cast downe the king.</l>
                  <l>So sore to ground he him cast, that his backe all to brast.</l>
                  <l>And had not soone come succour, he had then slaine king Iour.</l>
                  <l>They tooke the horse with much slight, and led him to the pallace right.</l>
                  <l>With great ropes they him bound, there was no meat before him found.</l>
                  <l>Neither otes nor water cleere, there he stood that seuen yeare.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:16"/>
                  <l>But that Iosian him brought, and that wist the king right nought.</l>
                  <l>For his men could not him read, with staruing for to haue him dead.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>IOsian is now Quéene, Beuis in prison with much déene.</l>
                  <l>Strange wordes were ther beforn, he cursed the time y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he was borne.</l>
                  <l>His haire hanged long and side, full simple then was his pride.</l>
                  <l>On a day Beuis would sléepe, an Adder great did on him créepe.</l>
                  <l>And stinged him sore without lye, vpon his brow aboue his eye.</l>
                  <l>Beuis waked and loud gan crye, and said Iesu my Lord mercie.</l>
                  <l>This Adder hath bitten me sore, out of my life I would I wore.</l>
                  <l>Helpe Lord and if it be thy will, and let me neuer in prison spill.</l>
                  <l>With that an Angell come is, and appeared vnto Beuis.</l>
                  <l>Gods Angell he saw by his slight, by whom the worme lost her sight.</l>
                  <l>And before him all to brast, Beuis saw it and laught fast.</l>
                  <l>Sir Beuis was féeble and faint, to Iesu Christ he made complaint.</l>
                  <l>And vnto his mother Mary, and rufully began to crye.</l>
                  <l>Lord he said of heauen King, that shapedst me and euery thing:</l>
                  <l>What offence haue I done to thée, that hence thou wilt not helpe me?</l>
                  <l>The Sarasines do me much woe, haue mercy on me O Lord do so.</l>
                  <l>Now giue me grace heauen to winne, and out of prison that I am in.</l>
                  <l>The two wardes heard his complaint, how féeble he was and how faint.</l>
                  <l>The one said hearest thou this felowne, how he dispiseth our Mahound?</l>
                  <l>He wéeneth that his God may him saue, and succour thinketh he to haue.</l>
                  <l>But by Mahound it shall not gaine, I shall not rest till he be slaine.</l>
                  <l>And sodainly at that word, he let a lampe downe by a cord.</l>
                  <l>And sayd, come downe when I call, to helpe what euer me befall.</l>
                  <l>Then a sword he tooke by his syde, and by the rope downe did glide:</l>
                  <l>And smote Beuis that stound, that he felled him to the ground.</l>
                  <l>Lord sayd Beuis, why dost thou so? now is my heart in full great woe.</l>
                  <l>Had I my sword good Morglay, and Arundell my good Palfray:</l>
                  <l>For all Damas with their treason, would I not giue one button.</l>
                  <l>And now the most wretch of all, at one stroke doth make me fall.</l>
                  <l>Now were I worthy to behanged, but if I were of it reuenged.</l>
                  <l>Beuis with his fist smote so fast, that his necke all to brast.</l>
                  <l>The other cryed that was aboue, and sayd fellow for my loue,</l>
                  <l>Hast thou of me any néede, that I may come thée to réede.</l>
                  <l>Yea sayd Beuis all for guile, come hether to me a litle while.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> I must néedes haue thy read, or that Beuis be all dead.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:16"/>
                  <l>The other Warden no longer abode, but downe the rope he slode.</l>
                  <l>And saw Beuis whole and sound, and his fellow dead on the ground.</l>
                  <l>He would haue fled vp that tide, nay said Beuis thou must abide.</l>
                  <l>Beuis with his fellowes brand, smote asunder through Gods hand,</l>
                  <l>The rope aboue the Sarasines head, that to prison to his fellow he yede.</l>
                  <l>Then was Beuis glad and faine, his two wardens he had slayne.</l>
                  <l>Thrée dayes he lay and nought eate, he thought that life nothing swéete.</l>
                  <l>Yet was Beuis wont each day, while that he in prison lay,</l>
                  <l>Of wheat bran to haue a messe, therewith his hunger to redresse.</l>
                  <l>But when his wardens were fordone, bread ne bran eat he none.</l>
                  <l>That pennance was full strong, he thought he liued all to long.</l>
                  <l>Iesu Christ sir <hi>Beuis</hi> said, helpe me with a litle bread.</l>
                  <l>The rope may I not reach, but if thou me wish or teach.</l>
                  <l>Too high he smote the rope asunder, if he it reach it were great wonder</l>
                  <l>But yet by Gods might, <hi>Beuis</hi> skipped he was ful light.</l>
                  <l>And gate the rope in his hand, and came vp I vnderstand.</l>
                  <l>When he came vp he saw no light, for it was about midnight.</l>
                  <l>But well he heard in the stable, Gromes sing and make bable.</l>
                  <l>Vnto the stable dore he went, and smote it open at a dint.</l>
                  <l>A doore barre he tooke in hand, and slew all that he there fand.</l>
                  <l>A good stéed then foorth he brought, and sadled him well ynough.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beuis</hi> rode to the gate ful euen, and called the Porter with milde steuen.</l>
                  <l>Rise Porter anon he said, <hi>Beuis</hi> of Hampton hath vs betraid.</l>
                  <l>Sone after the gates were vnlockt, and with that <hi>Beuis</hi> out lept.</l>
                  <l>The Porter straight his way tooke, vnto the prison for to looke.</l>
                  <l>He found the wardens slaine ywis, and <hi>Beuis</hi> foorth escaped is.</l>
                  <l>The Porter said, by my snout, the same was <hi>Beuis</hi> I let out.</l>
                  <l>The Porter went to the king and said, how that <hi>Beuis</hi> had him betrayd.</l>
                  <l>And slaine his wardens both in fear, the king made sorrow &amp; heuy cheare.</l>
                  <l>There were fiue kings in the Pallaice, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> made him homage y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> story saies.</l>
                  <l>To them Bradmoūd made his mone, they armed them euery one.</l>
                  <l>A knight there was proud and fierce, men called him sir Graunders.</l>
                  <l>An horse he had of great price, the which was called Trunchefice.</l>
                  <l>He was worth his weight in gold, he would so run vpon the molde.</l>
                  <l>Sir Graunders was the first dight, on Trunchefice vp he light,</l>
                  <l>And rode after sir <hi>Beuis,</hi> well he thought to winne the price.</l>
                  <l>When he was past Damace, he saw <hi>Beuis</hi> ride apace.</l>
                  <l>He said turne thée Dogges whelpe, thy God shall thée nothing helpe.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:17"/>
                  <l>Through thée shal I get renowne, if thou be Beuis of Southhamptowne.</l>
                  <l>Then Beuis vnto him did say: it is no maistry me to slay.</l>
                  <l>For if that here I slaine bée, it is through hunger, and not through thée.</l>
                  <l>But neuerthelesse we will assay, how well thou wilt thy duty pay.</l>
                  <l>Beuis turned him well and fayre, and rode together with great ayre.</l>
                  <l>Such a stroke he gaue Graundere, that through helme &amp; hauberke cléere,</l>
                  <l>Hart and bodie he claue asunder, there helped no armour, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> was wonder.</l>
                  <l>Right to the saddle, be head myne, he cloue him downe lyke a swyne.</l>
                  <l>Beuis Trunchefice soone bestrode, he left his owne and foorth he rode.</l>
                  <l>King Bradmound with all his hoast, came ryding after with great bost.</l>
                  <l>And so fast followed they, that Beuis was driuen to the sea.</l>
                  <l>He said, if I fight so many agayne, for hunger &amp; féeblenes I shal be slaine.</l>
                  <l>Yet will I to water flye ywis, and let God worke what his will is.</l>
                  <l>Then to be slayne among them all: helpe me Lord, for now I call.</l>
                  <l>Beuis made his horse to skippe, fortie foote in sea he leapt</l>
                  <l>The Sarasines saw that after came, how the horse with Beuis swame.</l>
                  <l>By the helpe of the Lord of might, the horse bare ouer that noble knight.</l>
                  <l>When he was the water past, the horse him rested and shoke him fast.</l>
                  <l>And for féeblenes in that stound, sir Beuis fell on the ground.</l>
                  <l>Lord sayd Beuis how hungry am I, and if I were king of Armony,</l>
                  <l>I would giue it without read, for one shiuer of browne bread.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>FOrth rode Beuis with great ayre, till he came to a castle fayre.</l>
                  <l>A Lady ouer the wall lay, dame sayd Beuis I thée pray,</l>
                  <l>For his loue that dyed on trée, one meales meat giue to me.</l>
                  <l>The Lady answeared him tho, from my gate I read thée goe.</l>
                  <l>An other place is better then here, for here thou gettest a cold dinner.</l>
                  <l>For my Lord is a Gyaunt, and beléeueth in Mahound and Termagaunt.</l>
                  <l>And if he know thou be a Christian, he will thée slay with much paine.</l>
                  <l>For God sayd Beuis, and swore an othe, whether he be liefe or loath,</l>
                  <l>Here will I meate eate, to dye therefore but I it get.</l>
                  <l>The Lady was abashed withall, and went downe into the hall:</l>
                  <l>And told her Lord that was so stout, how a man had sworne without.</l>
                  <l>That he would there eate his fill, in the despite of thy will.</l>
                  <l>Yea sayd the Gyaunt, will he so, a dore barre he tooke in his hand tho:</l>
                  <l>And out vnto sir Beuis he brayde, and thus vnto him he sayd.</l>
                  <l>What art thou fellow, art thou wise? where stolest thou Trunchefice?</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:17"/>
                  <l>
                     <figure/>
                  </l>
                  <l>That thou sittest vppon there, he was my brothers sir Grandere.</l>
                  <l>God knoweth then sayd Beuis, I shore sir Graunders crowne ywis.</l>
                  <l>When we met last in battayle, I made him Deacon withouten fayle.</l>
                  <l>And if that thou wilt order take, a Priest sayd Beuis I shall thée make.</l>
                  <l>Alas said the Gyaūt for sir Grandere, his death shalt thou abide ful déere.</l>
                  <l>To sir Beuis he smote full sore, but of Beuis he fay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> thore.</l>
                  <l>And hit Trunchefice in that stound, that he fell dead vnto the ground.</l>
                  <l>Beuis start vp without respite, and to the Gyant gan he smite.</l>
                  <l>Such a stroke was not sée<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e in no land, sithen Oliuer dyed and Rouland.</l>
                  <l>The Gyaunt saw y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Beuis was strong, he drew out a dart sharpe &amp; long.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:18"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:18"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:19"/>
                  <l>Through Beuis shoulder he did it shoote, the bloud ran downe to his foot.</l>
                  <l>When sir Beuis saw the bloud, for yre and téene he waxed wood.</l>
                  <l>He smote the Gyant then full ill, with all his might and all his will.</l>
                  <l>And such a stroke he him lent, that helme and head from body went.</l>
                  <l>Breast and bodie he cloue downe, with a stroke of his fawchowne.</l>
                  <l>Now sayd Beuis by Moone &amp; Sun, I trow my meat I haue wel woon.</l>
                  <l>Dame said Beuis stay no more, but giue me meat I hunger sore.</l>
                  <l>And thus much take thou of me, of meat and drinke no niggard bée.</l>
                  <l>The Lady durst not him withstand, she led Beuis by the hand.</l>
                  <l>And serued him of bread and wine, and afterward of meates fine.</l>
                  <l>And of each messe ywis, she brought vnto sir Beuis.</l>
                  <l>He made her eate first for thy, she should do him no villany.</l>
                  <l>And drinke the first of the wine, least she had put poyson therein.</l>
                  <l>When Beuis had eaten ynough, a white kerchife he drough.</l>
                  <l>And stopt therwith his wound, to stay the bléeding in that stound.</l>
                  <l>Beuis into the stable yéede, and sadled a goodly stéede.</l>
                  <l>There would he no longer abyde; he tooke his way and foorth did ryde.</l>
                  <l>Then sir Beuis foorth rode, till he came foorth all abroad,</l>
                  <l>Vnto a fayre gréene place, Lord sayd Beuis blessed be thy grace.</l>
                  <l>And now I wold that Bradmound king, were here w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> me &amp; al his spring,</l>
                  <l>On this gréene, men should sée, whether I would from him flie.</l>
                  <l>Foorth rode <hi>Beuis</hi> by the streame, till he came to Hierusalem.</l>
                  <l>And to the patriarch he went ful swift, and of his sinnes he him bereft.</l>
                  <l>Of Iosian to him he told the strife, that by right should haue bene his wife.</l>
                  <l>The Patriarch for his great truth, wept for him and thought great ruth.</l>
                  <l>He kept with him <hi>Beuis</hi> sole, till he was both sound and whole.</l>
                  <l>And forbode him on his life, that he should neuer wedde a wife.</l>
                  <l>But if she were a mayden cléene: nay sayd <hi>Beuis</hi> as I wéene.</l>
                  <l>When it came vnto the night <hi>Beuis</hi> tooke leaue like a gentle knight.</l>
                  <l>On the morow when it was day, <hi>Beuis</hi> rode foorth on his way.</l>
                  <l>And as he rode him selfe alone he bethought whither to gone.</l>
                  <l>Whether shall I to England fare, nay what should I do there.</l>
                  <l>Vnlesse I might an h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> gather, for to slay my stepfather.</l>
                  <l>I will he sayd to Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iony, to know the cause wherefore and why,</l>
                  <l>That the king did this treason, for my goodnes agaynst all reason.</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Beuis</hi> rode foorth right, he ouertooke another knight.</l>
                  <l>That would goe foorth to Arniony, and <hi>Beuis</hi> bare him company.</l>
                  <l>As they rode at the last, either beheld the other fast.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:19"/>
                  <l>And either then the other knew, for sometimes they were fellowes true.</l>
                  <l>Together they kissed after that, he asked <hi>Beuis</hi> of his estate.</l>
                  <l>God knoweth said <hi>Beuis</hi> and lough, I haue had sorrow ynough.</l>
                  <l>And suffered both hunger and cold, and other paines manifold.</l>
                  <l>Through the treason of king Ermine, &amp; sure I would requite his paine,</l>
                  <l>Were not his daughter Iosian, this day would I be his bane.</l>
                  <l>Iosian he said is a wife, against her will with much strife.</l>
                  <l>Seauen yeare it is by Termagant, sithen king Iour of Mambrant.</l>
                  <l>Iosian in Mambrant did wedde, both to boure and eke to bedde.</l>
                  <l>He hath thy sword good Morglay, and Arundell thy good palfray.</l>
                  <l>Where is Mambrant said <hi>Beuis</hi> thore? sir he said it is yonder before.</l>
                  <l>To Mambrāt ye can not reach to day, but turne you must another way.</l>
                  <l>Euer he rode foorth certaine, till he came to Mambrant plaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>MAmbrant is a ritch citie, faire and louely for to sée.</l>
                  <l>When sir <hi>Beuis</hi> of Southhamptowne, came within that ritch towne.</l>
                  <l>With a Palmer there he méet, full faire either other gan gréete.</l>
                  <l>Palmer he said where is the king? sir he said foorth on hunting.</l>
                  <l>With many knights stout and kéene, Palmer he said wher is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Quéene?</l>
                  <l>Sir he said in hir towre, Palmer he said Paramour,</l>
                  <l>Wilt thou giue me thy wéede, for my clothing and my stéede?</l>
                  <l>Would God sayd the Palmer, that ye had made that chaunge sir.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beuis</hi> gaue his horse fine, for the Palmers slauine.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beuis</hi> went to the castle gate, many Palmers he found thereat.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beuis</hi> said brethren déere, for what thing abide you here?</l>
                  <l>They answered him that there stood, we stand here to haue some good.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beuis</hi> said who shall it doe? the Quéene they said we beléeue so.</l>
                  <l>For all that she hath found here, euery day this seauen yeare,</l>
                  <l>Good chéere them doth shée make, once a day for Gods sake.</l>
                  <l>This almes giueth she by my crowne, for <hi>Beuis</hi> loue of Southhāptowne.</l>
                  <l>Then said <hi>Beuis</hi> for Christes lore, tell me now ye Palmers poore,</l>
                  <l>When this almes shall be done, sir they said at after noone.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beuis</hi> said it is but early day, he went from them anone away.</l>
                  <l>He thought he would goe spie and see, how that it might best bée.</l>
                  <l>As he came vnder a turret, that vnder the castle was set.</l>
                  <l>He heard Iosian wéepe and crye, thether he went for to spye.</l>
                  <l>Alas she said, for good <hi>Beuis,</hi> the gentle knight of Southampton is.</l>
                  <l>Alas shall I neuer sée that day, that once with him speake I may?</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:20"/>
                  <l>But Iesu Christ I take me till, helpe me and if it be thy will,</l>
                  <l>Euery day for seauen yeare, Iosian that Lady fayre,</l>
                  <l>Was wont such sorrow to make, for sir Beuis of Hamptons sake.</l>
                  <l>Soone she start to the gate thore, for to bring the Palmers poore.</l>
                  <l>Beuis hyed him fast to the gate, least he should haue come too late.</l>
                  <l>The Palmers pressed in fast, Beuis abode and was last.</l>
                  <l>To the hall she led them euery one, but vnto Beuis sayd Iosian anone.</l>
                  <l>Thou séemest most best to me, for I desire to talke with thée.</l>
                  <l>Begin thou the boord Palmer, and merily goe thou vnto thy dinner.</l>
                  <l>When the Palmers were all set, meate and drinke she did them fet.</l>
                  <l>Then gan she to Beuis say, tell me Palmer now by thy fay,</l>
                  <l>Hast thou heard any man tell, in any land where it befell,</l>
                  <l>Either in field or towne, of sir Beuis of Southhamptowne?</l>
                  <l>I shall make them ritch without leasing, that of him can tell any thing.</l>
                  <l>Yea Dame said Beuis and lough, sir Beuis I know well ynough.</l>
                  <l>At home in his countrie, I am an Earle and so is he.</l>
                  <l>For he loueth me ouer all, for either was other promigall.</l>
                  <l>At home he gan me much to tell, of an horse that hight Arundell.</l>
                  <l>I haue asked in many a land, for that horse I vnderstand.</l>
                  <l>And sought him both farre and néere, and each man sayth he is here.</l>
                  <l>As yée loue that same knight, of that horse let me haue sight.</l>
                  <l>The Quéene without any fable, led Beuis into the stable.</l>
                  <l>The Quéene gan Beuis behold, and vnto Boniface she told.</l>
                  <l>I trow she sayd by my crowne, this is Beuis of Southhamptowne.</l>
                  <l>But Beuis beard was neuer shorne, since he was of his mother borne.</l>
                  <l>When Beuis into the stable came, anone to Arundell he ranne,</l>
                  <l>And sayd Arundell God thée saue, without the towne I would thée haue.</l>
                  <l>With thée came I neuer to Mābrant, but w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> me thou shouldest to Englād.</l>
                  <l>Arundell in sunder burst chaines seauen, when he heard sir Beuis steuē.</l>
                  <l>And foorth he ranne out of the place, and neyghed and made great race.</l>
                  <l>Alas sayd Iosian tho, for Arundell I am full woe.</l>
                  <l>For he will be many a mans bane, or that he agayne be tane.</l>
                  <l>Nay sayd Beuis and lough, I can take him well ynough.</l>
                  <l>If that yée will geue me leaue, I shall him take without griefe.</l>
                  <l>To take the horse she him prayed, and lead him vp the Lady sayd.</l>
                  <l>That there be no more distaunce, with that I shall thée aduaunce.</l>
                  <l>I graunt sayd Beuis by Gods dome, whē Arundel saw his maister come,</l>
                  <l>He would neuer start nor leape, till Beuis on his backe did skippe.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:20"/>
                  <l>Beuis on Arundels backe he threw, and thereby Iosian him knew.</l>
                  <l>She sayd <hi>Beuis</hi> loue déere, ride not from me in no manner.</l>
                  <l>Thou promised me to wife to take, when I my false gods did forsake.</l>
                  <l>Helpe <hi>Beuis</hi> at this néede, for thou hast Arundell thy stéede.</l>
                  <l>I shall fetch thy sword Morglay, and lead me with thée away.</l>
                  <l>Said <hi>Beuis</hi> thou mightest me blame, it may me turne vnto shame.</l>
                  <l>I lay for thée in prison strong, seauen winters that was long.</l>
                  <l>And the Patriarch on my life, charged me neuer to take wife.</l>
                  <l>But she were a maiden cléene. And seauē yeare thou hast bene a Quéene.</l>
                  <l>And euery night a knight by thée, how shouldest thou a mayden bée?</l>
                  <l>Mercie sir <hi>Beuis</hi> then sayd she, haue me home to your countrie.</l>
                  <l>If you finde me not a true woman, in all that you say can,</l>
                  <l>Send me hether to my foe, my selfe all naked and no moe.</l>
                  <l>I graunt quoth <hi>Beuis</hi> that thou do goe, on the couenant that it be so.</l>
                  <l>Hye thée fast and make thée prest, and if with me goe thou list.</l>
                  <l>Boniface stood a litle beside, and said sir it were best abide.</l>
                  <l>Sir <hi>Beuis</hi> he sayd it is great perill, yée shall be taught a better skill.</l>
                  <l>The king is gone on his playing, and soone he wil come fro hunting.</l>
                  <l>And if he finde we be away, he will pursue vs night and day,</l>
                  <l>With all his great chiualrie, of courage stout and hardie.</l>
                  <l>Yée shall be drawne through the towne, and hanged as a false felowne.</l>
                  <l>Sir <hi>Beuis</hi> I do you read, Arundell to stable yée lead.</l>
                  <l>And at the gate ye shall abyde, for when the king doth in ride,</l>
                  <l>He wil aske you of tydinges, where you haue bene and in what landes.</l>
                  <l>Yée shall tell him redely, that you came out of Surry.</l>
                  <l>And that the land is greatly noyed, townes be burnt and men distroyed.</l>
                  <l>And that king Bradwine is, in point to loose his landes ywis.</l>
                  <l>Through Siracke and his men, of Antioch the ritch citie then.</l>
                  <l>Looke yée tell him none other, for king Bradwine is his brother.</l>
                  <l>And when he heareth this tyding, he wil goe thether with great hasting.</l>
                  <l>With all his power and all his hoast, then may we goe with litle boast.</l>
                  <l>Now sayd <hi>Beuis</hi> I hould me appayed, he led vp his horse as he sayd.</l>
                  <l>Soone after came the king from hunting, and of <hi>Beuis</hi> he asked tyding.</l>
                  <l>And all to him told <hi>Beuis</hi> thore, as Boniface told him before.</l>
                  <l>I haue great wōder said king Iour, that he sendeth not hether for succour.</l>
                  <l>The messengers were taken fiue, sir sayd <hi>Beuis</hi> by my life,</l>
                  <l>That came from king Bradwine, I tell thée by Gods payne.</l>
                  <l>King Siracke hath them in hould, I trow it be not Bradwine told.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:21"/>
                  <l>Now said king Iour, I will hye me to that stoure.</l>
                  <l>For all I can to helpe my brother, in his right against the other,</l>
                  <l>King Iour gathered a great partie, foorth he went into Surry.</l>
                  <l>But his steward sir Grassy, he left at home full readily.</l>
                  <l>Then came together in that case, <hi>Beuis,</hi> Iosian and Boniface.</l>
                  <l>Now it is time said <hi>Beuis</hi> to goe, nay said Boniface, ye shal not do so.</l>
                  <l>The kings steward sir Grassy, is made kéeper of my Lady.</l>
                  <l>I know a grasse said he ywis, that of such vertue is,</l>
                  <l>All those that thereof drinke, it shall make their eies to winke.</l>
                  <l>And make them sléepe through might, all a day and all a nyght.</l>
                  <l>Had Grassy dronk this grasse in wine, thē might we goe w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> coūsail mine.</l>
                  <l>When Boniface had done this thing, vp he rose without leasing.</l>
                  <l>On the morow withouten misse, Iosian, Boniface, and Beuis,</l>
                  <l>They them puruayed as they wold, both of siluer and of gold.</l>
                  <l>They hyed them foorth on their way, sir Grassy awoke on the other day.</l>
                  <l>When he wist y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Quéene was gone, with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Palmer he made great mone.</l>
                  <l>He made his men them to dight, and gathered great power for to fight.</l>
                  <l>Then he rode foorth all by déene, after the Palmer and the Quéene.</l>
                  <l>All Mambrant after them drough, weapened and armed well ynough.</l>
                  <l>On euery syde a great rout, they beset Beuis round about,</l>
                  <l>Then said Beuis to Boniface, thou séest we be in strange case.</l>
                  <l>Thou shalt with hir abide here still, till I goe fight with them my fill.</l>
                  <l>They shall abye if that I may, for I haue rested many a day.</l>
                  <l>Had you neuer so good gaming, as ye shall sée when we are lamming.</l>
                  <l>Nay sayd Boniface to him tho, forsooth it shall not be so.</l>
                  <l>I shall you bring in lesse doubt, the land is beset round about.</l>
                  <l>A litle beside vs here, is a caue in a rocke néere.</l>
                  <l>Were we once, therein brought, we néede not care for them ought.</l>
                  <l>To the caue they came at last, Grassy searched and ouer them past.</l>
                  <l>He went againe where he came fro, with great care and much woe.</l>
                  <l>All night in that caue they were, without meat or drinke there.</l>
                  <l>Iosian hungred on the morow sore, &amp; to sir Beuis she complained thore.</l>
                  <l>Beuis sayd to Boniface, kéepe thou Iosian in this place.</l>
                  <l>For I will goe vpon this hill, to sée if I may ought kill,</l>
                  <l>That we may on coales cast, for Iosian may euill fast.</l>
                  <l>Foorth went Beuis in that stound, with him he led a good greyhound.</l>
                  <l>And when sir Beuis went them fro, within the caue came Lyons two.</l>
                  <l>Grenning &amp; ramping with their féet, &amp; both on Boniface did they leape.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:21"/>
                  <l>His horse vnto him he drought, and armed him well ynough.</l>
                  <l>And gaue vnto them battayle right, but all too féeble was his might.</l>
                  <l>For anone they him slew, and his horse all to gnew.</l>
                  <l>When they had eaten of that man, they went both to Iosian.</l>
                  <l>And layd their heads vppon hir arme, but they would do hir no harme.</l>
                  <l>For it is the Lyons kinde ywis, a kinges daughter that mayd is,</l>
                  <l>Harme ne scath none to doe, therefore lay the lyons so.</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Beuis</hi> came from hunting, in the caue at the beginning.</l>
                  <l>As he went in for the nones, saw a man gnawen to the bones,</l>
                  <l>Into the caue then went he, to sée what chaunce there might bée.</l>
                  <l>Iosian sate in much doubt, and two Lyons hir about.</l>
                  <l>A sir sayd Iosian tho, come and reuenge of these two.</l>
                  <l>For right now haue they slayne, Boniface your chamberlaine.</l>
                  <l>The one Lyon will I hold, whyles yée make the other cold.</l>
                  <l>About the necke shée tooke the one, and <hi>Beuis</hi> bad hir let him goe.</l>
                  <l>I say Iosian let them be, for I sée well a mayden be yée.</l>
                  <l>What maistry is it them to slo, in handes when ye hold them so?</l>
                  <l>Let them come to me both, or els forsooth I will be wroth.</l>
                  <l>She let goe the Lyon without misse, and both they assaulted sir <hi>Beuis.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>strong and perillous was the fight, betwéene the Lyons and the knight.</l>
                  <l>They gaue him wounds long &amp; wide, his armour they tore on euery side.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beuis</hi> thereat was fell and wroth, at one stroke he slew them both.</l>
                  <l>For Boniface full woe was he, but when he saw no boot would bée.</l>
                  <l>He tooke vp Iosian that tyde, and on his way foorth gan ride.</l>
                  <l>They had not ridden but a while, not the mountenance of a mile.</l>
                  <l>But they met with a Gyaunt, with a full sory semblaunt.</l>
                  <l>He was both mighty and strong, he was full thirtie foot long.</l>
                  <l>He was bristeled like a sow, a foot there was betwéene each brow.</l>
                  <l>His lips wer great they hāged aside, his eies were holow his mouth wide.</l>
                  <l>He was lothly to looke on, he was lyker a deuill then a man.</l>
                  <l>His staffe was a yong Oke, he would giue a great stroke.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beuis</hi> wondrod I you plight, and asked him what he hight.</l>
                  <l>My name sayd he is Ascapart, sir Grassy sent me hetherward,</l>
                  <l>For to bring you home agayne, and now I am glad and fayne,</l>
                  <l>That I haue you here found, for together you shall be bound.</l>
                  <l>So shall you be led to Mambrant, with a full sory semblant.</l>
                  <l>Yet sayd <hi>Beuis,</hi> thou maist faile, by me thou mayst dye in battaile.</l>
                  <l>Of Arundell <hi>Beuis</hi> downe light, and tooke him to his Lady bright.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:22"/>
                  <l>And Beuis with a bould hart, with Morglay assayled Ascapart.</l>
                  <l>Betwixt them two was great fight, sir Beuis was nimble and light.</l>
                  <l>And start away his dint fro, when Ascapart at him did throw.</l>
                  <l>If his hart would brast, he could not one on Beuis fast.</l>
                  <l>For if he had smitten sir Beuis ones, he would haue brast all his bones.</l>
                  <l>
                     <figure/>
                  </l>
                  <l>Beuis skipped here and thore, and gaue him woundes wide and sore.</l>
                  <l>Then Ascapart was full woe, and smote at sir Beuis tho.</l>
                  <l>He smote to hit sir Beuis crowne, his foot slipt and he fell downe.</l>
                  <l>And ere that he aryse might, Beuis with his sword was dight,</l>
                  <l>To haue smitten off his head, but Iosian did it forbidde.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:22"/>
                  <l>Sir she said ye shall him saue, and let him liue to be our knaue,</l>
                  <l>Dame he saide he will vs betray, I will be his borow she said nay,</l>
                  <l>Ascapart made Beuis homage, and became sir Beuis page,</l>
                  <l>Then they went foorth all thrée, till they came vnto the sea.</l>
                  <l>A dromound they found there, to Christendome ready they were,</l>
                  <l>
                     <figure/>
                  </l>
                  <l>There were Sarasines great plenty, and warned Beuis there to be,</l>
                  <l>When Ascapart heard of that, anone to him he tooke his bat,</l>
                  <l>He droue them out with much harme, &amp; bare Arundell vnder his arme,</l>
                  <l>Beuis &amp; Iosian to shippe he bare, he drew vp sayle and made them fare,</l>
                  <l>They sayled foorth south to sine, vnto the heauen of Coleyne.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:23"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beuis</hi> went into the land, and soone a friend there he fand,</l>
                  <l>The bishop of the towne Percas, to sir <hi>Beuis</hi> sibbe he was,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beuis</hi> gréet well the bishop bold, and what he was he him told,</l>
                  <l>The bishop then was well apayd, my déere cosin welcome he sayd.</l>
                  <l>To sée you heere I am full fayne, my minde gaue me you wer slayne,</l>
                  <l>Whence he sayd is thy Lady shéene, sir <hi>Beuis</hi> said in Heathenes a quéene,</l>
                  <l>For her I haue suffered much payne, &amp; she wuld become a Christian fayne</l>
                  <l>He said what is this bad visage, sir said <hi>Beuis</hi> he is my page.</l>
                  <l>He must be christened also, though he be both blacke and blo,</l>
                  <l>The bishop Christened Iosian, that was as white as any swanne,</l>
                  <l>For Ascapart was made a Phunt, and when he should therein be put,</l>
                  <l>He lept ouer the bench, and said churle wilt thou me drench,</l>
                  <l>The diuell of hell thy bane be, I am too much to be chrstened of thee,</l>
                  <l>The folke had good game and lough, but the bishop was wroth inough.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Beuis slew a fierce and dreadfull Dragon in the Land of Colayne.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>NOw is <hi>Beuis</hi> in Colayne land, through the might of Christs hand,</l>
                  <l>There he gate great renowne, by the slaying of a Dragon,</l>
                  <l>For whē Launcelot du lake, fought with the burning drake,</l>
                  <l>Guy of Warwike I vnderstand, slew a Dragon in England,</l>
                  <l>But such a Dragon was neuer séene, as sir <hi>Beuis</hi> slew men wéene,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beuis</hi> went to bed at night, with much ioy and torch bright,</l>
                  <l>And after his first sleeping, he heard a rufull crying,</l>
                  <l>The voice sayd in his cry, Iesu my Lord on me haue mercy.</l>
                  <l>I rotte he saide bone by bone, my death is comming me vpon,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beuis</hi> therefore had great sorow, he asked them there on the morow,</l>
                  <l>He asked them what was the cry, they aunswered and told why,</l>
                  <l>They sayd it was a noble knight, that was strong and bolde in fight.</l>
                  <l>And as he rode through the towne, he met with a fell Dragon,</l>
                  <l>That with venime on him throwne, the knight lay all to blowne,</l>
                  <l>And I shall tell you all the case, how the Dragon came to this place,</l>
                  <l>In the towne of Calaboure men tell, where two Dragons great &amp; fell,</l>
                  <l>These two Dragons there can fight, seuen yéere both day and night,</l>
                  <l>And destroyed both man and beast, on euery side both west and East,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:23"/>
                  <l>
                     <figure/>
                  </l>
                  <l>Ther was one in that land, that was full of Gods sond,</l>
                  <l>He made request to God aboue, thut he should for his mothers loue,</l>
                  <l>Delyuer out by his holy grace, these two Dragons from this place,</l>
                  <l>Then these two Dragons down fell, they had no power there to dwell,</l>
                  <l>Than they flew to Tuscayne, many men there haue they slayne,</l>
                  <l>From Thuskaine into Lomberdy, there they did great villany,</l>
                  <l>The one Dragon by Gods dome, flew to the court of Rome,</l>
                  <l>He there rested his coursed bones, some say in a caue of stones,</l>
                  <l>Men say he is there yet, enclosed with Clearkes wit,</l>
                  <l>The other Dragon we vnderstand, flew hither into Colayne land,</l>
                  <l>Within a mile lyeth he, but a mile from the sea,</l>
                  <l>All Colayne Land round about, haue of him great doubt,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:24"/>
                  <l>That Dragon was heere this night, &amp; hath destroyed the said knight,</l>
                  <l>Lord Christ side Beuis tho, may no man that Dragon slo,</l>
                  <l>Certaine they sayd without fable, all Christendom is not for him able,</l>
                  <l>But if Michaell came downe, shall no man slay that Dragon,</l>
                  <l>Sir Beuis called Ascapart him to, and asked him what to do,</l>
                  <l>And sayd wilt thou with me go, for to see that Dragon wee two,</l>
                  <l>by chaunce if wee with him fight, we may him slay by Gods might,</l>
                  <l>I am ready sayd Ascapart truely, haue done anone let vs thether hye.</l>
                  <l>Beuis armed him &amp; foorth did ride, and Ascapart by his side,</l>
                  <l>When they were past the Citie, and were néere where he should be,</l>
                  <l>The Dragon cast vp such a yell, that would haue feared the diuel of hell,</l>
                  <l>Ascapart said with heauy chéere, hearest thou what I do heare,</l>
                  <l>Yes said Beuis haue no doubt, the Dragon is héere about,</l>
                  <l>Boldly shall we to him goe, by Gods grace we shall him slo,</l>
                  <l>Beuis rode foorth a good pace, where he trowed the Dragon was,</l>
                  <l>Forsooth saide Ascapart tho, I will homewards againe goe.</l>
                  <l>For I would not for all Pauy, sée that diuell that made that cry,</l>
                  <l>What diuel said <hi>Beuis</hi> art thou mad, I thought nothing might make thee adrad</l>
                  <l>For shame wilt thou afrayed be, of any thing or thou it sée,</l>
                  <l>Sir he said with heuy chéere, I will him neuer sée nor heare,</l>
                  <l>Well said Beuis wilt thou so, I will him slay or I go,</l>
                  <l>Ascapart furder would he nought, but Beuis rode foorth and sought,</l>
                  <l>And when the Dragon that foule is, had a sight of sir Beuis,</l>
                  <l>He cast vp a loud cry, as it had thundred in the sky.</l>
                  <l>He turned his belly toward the sun, it was bigger then any tunne,</l>
                  <l>His scales wes brighter then the glasse, &amp; harder they wer thē any brasse,</l>
                  <l>betwéene his shoulder and his tayle, was forty foote without fayle,</l>
                  <l>He weltred out of his den, and Beuis pricked his stéede then,</l>
                  <l>And to him a speare he thrust, that all to shiuers it brust,</l>
                  <l>The Dragon gan Beuis assayle, &amp; smot sir Beuis with his tayle,</l>
                  <l>Then downe went horse and man, two ribbes of Beuis brused than,</l>
                  <l>Vp start Beuis with good will, and after ranne the Dragon till,</l>
                  <l>And good Morglay out brayd, and on the Dragon fast he layd,</l>
                  <l>but for no stroke that he did strike, would not Morglay on him bite,</l>
                  <l>The Dragon was gréeued sore, and smote at Beuis more and more</l>
                  <l>And gaue him many a great wound, and felled him oft to the ground,</l>
                  <l>What for wery and what for faint, sir Beuis was néere attaint,</l>
                  <l>The Dragon sewed on Beuis so hard, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> as he would haue fled backwrd,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:24"/>
                  <l>There was a well as I wéene, and he stumbed right therein,</l>
                  <l>Then was Beuis afrayed and woe, lest the Dragon should him slo,</l>
                  <l>Or that he might away passe, when he in that well was,</l>
                  <l>Then was the well of such vertue, through the might of Christ Iesu.</l>
                  <l>For sometime dwelled in that lond, a Virgin full of Christs sond,</l>
                  <l>That had bene bathed in that well, that euer after as men tell,</l>
                  <l>Might no venimous worme come therein, by the vertue of that Virgin,</l>
                  <l>Nigh it seauen foote and more, then Beuis was glad therefore,</l>
                  <l>When he sawe the Dragon fell, had no power to come to the well,</l>
                  <l>Then was he glad without fayle, and rested a while for his auayle,</l>
                  <l>And dranke of that water his fill, and then he lept out with good will,</l>
                  <l>And with Morglay his brand, assayled the Dragon I vnderstand,</l>
                  <l>On the Dragon he smote so fast, where that he hit the scales brast,</l>
                  <l>The Dragon than faynted sore, and cast a galon and more,</l>
                  <l>Out of his mouth of venime strong, and one sir Beuis he it flong,</l>
                  <l>Which was so venimous ywis, that when it was on sir Beuis.</l>
                  <l>His armour burst in that stound, and he fell dead to the ground,</l>
                  <l>There was no life on him séene, he lay as a dead man on the gréene,</l>
                  <l>The Dragon smot him without faile, that he tourned top and tayle,</l>
                  <l>but thereoff he tooke no kéepe, he lay as a dead man on sléepe,</l>
                  <l>He smote Beuis as I you tell, the dint smote him into the well,</l>
                  <l>That was of great vertue that time, for it would suffer no venime,</l>
                  <l>Through vertue of the Virgin, that once was bathed therin,</l>
                  <l>When Beuis was at the ground, the water made him whole &amp; sound,</l>
                  <l>And quenched all the venim away, this well saued Beuis that day,</l>
                  <l>When he féelt him whole and light, and knew that well of great might</l>
                  <l>Then was he a ioyfull man, he was as fresh as when he began,</l>
                  <l>He knéeled downe in that place, to Iesu Christ he called for grace,</l>
                  <l>That he would send him might, to slay the Dragon in fight,</l>
                  <l>Beuis blessed him and foorth yode, and lept out with hart full good,</l>
                  <l>And Beuis to the Dragon gone is, and the Dragon also to <hi>Beuis,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Long and hard was the fight, betwext the Dragon and the knight,</l>
                  <l>But euer whē <hi>Beuis</hi> was hurt sore, he went to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> wel &amp; washed him thore,</l>
                  <l>He was as whole as any man, &amp; euer as fresh as when he began,</l>
                  <l>The Dragon saw y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> might not auayle, beside the well to hold battaile,</l>
                  <l>He thought he would with some wile, out of that place <hi>Beuis</hi> beguile,</l>
                  <l>He would haue flowen thē away, &amp; <hi>Beuis</hi> lept after with good Morglay,</l>
                  <l>And hit him vnder the wing, as he was in his flying,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:25"/>
                  <l>There he was tender without skale, and <hi>Beuis</hi> thought to be his bale,</l>
                  <l>He smote after as I you say, with his good sword Morglay,</l>
                  <l>Vp to the hilts Morglay yode, through hart, liuer, bone and bloud,</l>
                  <l>To the ground fell the Dragon, great ioy sir <hi>Beuis</hi> begon.</l>
                  <l>Vnder the scales all on hight, he smote his head foorth right,</l>
                  <l>And put it vpon a speare, and vnneth he might it beare,</l>
                  <l>He went to Colaine that tide, with great ioy and much pride,</l>
                  <l>When they of the citie sawe <hi>Beuis,</hi> come with the dragons head ywis,</l>
                  <l>All the bells gan they ring, priestes and clearkes then did sing,</l>
                  <l>And brought <hi>Beuis</hi> to the towne, with procession and renowne,</l>
                  <l>Then was <hi>Beuis</hi> name in honour, euery man had him in fauour,</l>
                  <l>In euery land is spred, sir Beuis price and laud,</l>
                  <l>Glad was the Bishop tho, that sir Beuis had borne him so,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>¶ Beuis did goe vpon a day, to the bishop where he lay,</l>
                  <l>And sayd what is your réede sir, I would go venge my father,</l>
                  <l>Of that wicked felon, that slew him by treason,</l>
                  <l>If I might by any ginne, my herytage agayne to winne,</l>
                  <l>And sir ye be my fathers brother, and sir Sabere is the other,</l>
                  <l>Of you two I must haue counsaile, for surely I will him assaile,</l>
                  <l>Sir saide the Bishop anone right, sir Sabere is a doughty knight,</l>
                  <l>For euery yéere a day certayne, he fighteth thy stepfather agayne,</l>
                  <l>With a great baronage, for to winne thine heritage,</l>
                  <l>I wil thée finde at my costage, an hundred at my wage,</l>
                  <l>And go to Sabere thy eame right, he is in the yle of wight,</l>
                  <l>Sir he sayd God haue mercy, but let these men soone be ready,</l>
                  <l>Sir Beuis rode foorth to Iosian, and tooke his leaue of his lemman,</l>
                  <l>And siaid my Lady I must goe, for to wreake me of my foe,</l>
                  <l>For to winne vnto my hand, all my heritage and my land,</l>
                  <l>And héere still shall you be, and Ascapart shall be with thée,</l>
                  <l>Ye shall haue or I wend, mony ynough for to spend,</l>
                  <l>Iosian saw it would not be so, she kissed him and foorth go,</l>
                  <l>Forth went Beuis with his rout, of hardy men, bolde and stout,</l>
                  <l>That the bishop him gaue, so long on the sea they draue,</l>
                  <l>Till they came to the towne, but two mile from southhampton,</l>
                  <l>Then said Beuis to them tho, is héere any man that will goe,</l>
                  <l>Vnto sir Murdure of Almayne, and saye there is come an Almaine,</l>
                  <l>With doughty knights without distaunce, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> best of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> realme of Fraunce,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:25"/>
                  <l>And say we be come into this land, for we be done to vnderstand,</l>
                  <l>There should be great war &amp; fight, betwéene him and a nother knight,</l>
                  <l>And he will with him holde, we will defend him be he so bould,</l>
                  <l>And if he will not do so, we will to the other go,</l>
                  <l>A knight went foorth on that message, that gentle was of lynage,</l>
                  <l>When he came to the Castell gate, the porter let him in thereat,</l>
                  <l>And to sir Murdure was he lad, and told him as Beuis bad,</l>
                  <l>Murdure then was full faine, he rose vp and went them agayne,</l>
                  <l>And brought sir Beuis into the hall, and fayre saluted them all,</l>
                  <l>Beuis was sir Murdures fere, forsooth that night at supper,</l>
                  <l>His owne mother without leasing, made sir Beuis great feasting,</l>
                  <l>Murdure asked what he hight, Geraurd he said you plight,</l>
                  <l>Geraurd he sayd ywis, this Countes had or this,</l>
                  <l>And Earle her had or I hir wed, he gate a child by her in bed,</l>
                  <l>When the Earle to death was brought, the boy anone waxed nought,</l>
                  <l>His father was of noble bloud, and his mother in all things good,</l>
                  <l>The boy when he came to age, solde to me his heritage,</l>
                  <l>He spent his siluer with much blame, and went out of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> land for shame,</l>
                  <l>Now commeth his vncle an hardy knight, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> dwelleth in the yle of Wight</l>
                  <l>And challengeth his heritage, with a full bould baronage,</l>
                  <l>And often times with his great rout, destroyeth our land round about,</l>
                  <l>This is the cause sir Gerard, that eiher warre on other so hard,</l>
                  <l>When sir Murdure had all said, Beuis sat still and was euell apayed,</l>
                  <l>And thought Lord whether shall I slo, this false traytour or I goe.</l>
                  <l>Nay sayd Beuis and why, it will turne me to villany,</l>
                  <l>For men might déeme by reason, that I him slew by treason,</l>
                  <l>It would me tourne to cowardise, if I him slay in this wise,</l>
                  <l>Therefore I will not assaile, I will him slaye in playne battaile,</l>
                  <l>When Beuis a while had sitten still, sir he sayd will you heare my skill</l>
                  <l>I haue hither company brought, but in armour be the nought,</l>
                  <l>They might not with them armour lede, but it noyed them as they yede,</l>
                  <l>And few horses ywis haue we, we left for caryage on the sea,</l>
                  <l>Lend me horse and armour then, for to harneis all my men,</l>
                  <l>And if we haue shipping so, and that we may to the yle goe,</l>
                  <l>This night will I liue or dye, on them that is mine enimie,</l>
                  <l>And so within a lyttle whyle, you shall heare a quaynt guyle.</l>
                  <l>Sir Murdure did as he bad, and the men with armour clad,</l>
                  <l>And ordeyned them shipping good, and brought them vnto the flood,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:26"/>
                  <l>And foorth they went all by light, till they came to the yle of Wight,</l>
                  <l>Sabere out of his Castel lay, and hard much noyse and great aray,</l>
                  <l>And saw a ship to land was right, w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> an hundred heads w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> helms bright,</l>
                  <l>And had wonder what they were, but Beuis displayed his banner there.</l>
                  <l>For to make glad sir Sabere, of his father sir Guyes armere,</l>
                  <l>For many a time there beforne, were those armes in battaile borne,</l>
                  <l>Sabere knew the cognisaunce, and then he made good semblaunce,</l>
                  <l>And said certis I vnderstand, that yonder is Beuis commen to land,</l>
                  <l>Sabere went thether all in hast, where the ship was made fast,</l>
                  <l>And welcomed <hi>Beuis</hi> with ioy &amp; blisse, and either of them other kisse,</l>
                  <l>And thanked God of his grace, that <hi>Beuis</hi> was come to that place,</l>
                  <l>Forth went <hi>Beuis</hi> with Sabere, with their men all in feare,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beuis</hi> tould his eame there, how he deceiued his stepfather,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beuis</hi> asked foorthwith than, if there were euer a man,</l>
                  <l>The which dare goe as hote, vnto Southhampton in a bote,</l>
                  <l>And tell Murdure this night, that he was not a french knight.</l>
                  <l>Neither that he hight Gerrard, that made with him that forward,</l>
                  <l>But say he was <hi>Beuis</hi> of renowne, right heyre to Southhampton,</l>
                  <l>And say the Countesse is my dame, the diuell giue them both shame,</l>
                  <l>And say he will aduenged be, for slaying of his father sir Guy.</l>
                  <l>And who so will do for me this, shalbe well rewarded iwis,</l>
                  <l>vp start a knight with bold visage, which vndertooke that message,</l>
                  <l>And armed him all so hote, and went soone into a bote,</l>
                  <l>When he came to the other side, vnto the Castle did he ride.</l>
                  <l>And found sir Murdure at his supper, with good semblaunt &amp; great chéere,</l>
                  <l>The knight on his knées him set, and sir Murdure fayre he gréete,</l>
                  <l>And said sir Murdure I bring, this for a certeine tiding,</l>
                  <l>That the knight is not Gerrard, that made with thee this forward,</l>
                  <l>He hight <hi>Beuis</hi> of Southhampton, he is the Ladyes owne sonne,</l>
                  <l>I heard him so to Sabere speake, his fathers death he will wreake,</l>
                  <l>And winne he will his heritage, on thē y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> haue done him outrage,</l>
                  <l>When sir Murdure heard that word, he cast his knife ouer boord,</l>
                  <l>To haue smitten the messenger, but he fayled as you may heare,</l>
                  <l>And smote his sonne on the brest, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he neuer spake w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> clearke nor priest,</l>
                  <l>Then rose there a noyse and cry, the messenger then not for folly,</l>
                  <l>Thought not good to dwell there long, but out he lept them among.</l>
                  <l>And smote his horse with the spures, and sprang out at the doores,</l>
                  <l>Faire and well he gan him dight, till he came to the yle of Wight,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:26"/>
                  <l>And tould sir Beuis and sir Sabere, how sir Murdure sat at supper,</l>
                  <l>His owne sonne for yre he slough, Beuis had good game and lough,</l>
                  <l>And gaue the messenger in hand, sixty Floryes for his tydan.d</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How a knight that hight Miles came &amp; woed Iosian; and wedded her against her will.<figure/>
               </head>
               <l>LEt we of them be still than, and speake we now of Iosian,</l>
               <l>That in Colayne dwelled still, where she had not all her will,</l>
               <l>There dwelled a knight y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> hight Mile, in the land of Colayne y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> while,</l>
               <l>To Iosian his loue he cast, and woed her wondrous fast,</l>
               <l>But al his speach tourned to nought, for nothing cold chaūge hir thought</l>
               <l>The earle was wroth in his manner, for Iosian made him in great danger</l>
               <l>And in his anger he downe him set, &amp; to Iosian spake words great,</l>
               <l>I shall do with thée my will, whether it make the well or ill,</l>
               <l>Sir sayd Iosian thy best let be, I dread thée nought so may I thée,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:12215:27"/>
               <l>For if thou goe to my hart, I affye me in Ascapart.</l>
               <l>Certis though Earle Mile, I shall him some manner beguile.</l>
               <l>When he saw he migh not spéede, vp he rose and foorth yede.</l>
               <l>He made a letter be written right, on this manner it was dight.</l>
               <l>From Beuis as the letter would, that Ascapart come should.</l>
               <l>Vnto a Castle in an yle, being from Colayne but a myle.</l>
               <l>When Ascapart heard that sond, he tooke a bat in his hand.</l>
               <l>And went foorth with the messenger, in great hast till he came there.</l>
               <l>When he was well within, the messenger knew a quaint gin.</l>
               <l>Within he left Ascapart, and locked the gates to him hard.</l>
               <l>He rowed himselfe to land againe, and tould sir Myles of that traine.</l>
               <l>Then had the Earle no dread, but againe to Iosian yede.</l>
               <l>And said Lady make no mone, for Ascapart is from the gone.</l>
               <l>In a Castle within the sea, fast locked sure is he.</l>
               <l>Then was she full ill apaied, and to a messenger she saide.</l>
               <l>Go thou to ship this ylke night, and passe foorth to the yle of Wight.</l>
               <l>And bid sir <hi>Beuis</hi> for any thing, come to me without letting.</l>
               <l>And he will haue me on liue, therefore do thou go blyue.</l>
               <l>I shall thée thy reward pay, do thy errand without delay,</l>
               <l>The messenger went foorth away, there was no more then to say,</l>
               <l>And sir Mile after than, came vnto fayre Iosian.</l>
               <l>And first would haue lyne her by, good sir she said graunt me mercy.</l>
               <l>For I haue sworne by God truly, that no man shall lye me by.</l>
               <l>Although therefore I lose my life, vntil he wedde me as his wife,</l>
               <l>And thou wilt me spouse and wed, thou shalt haue me to thy bedde.</l>
               <l>Gladly my Lady then said he, to morrow shall we wedded be.</l>
               <l>He kissed her anone as his rights, and sent after barons and knights.</l>
               <l>That should be of his priuitie, at his wedding for to be.</l>
               <l>For he would be wedded priuely, the next morning very early,</l>
               <l>On the morrow he forgot nought, but they to the church were brought.</l>
               <l>They earely them began to wedde, both to boord and eke to bedde,</l>
               <l>When the wedding was all done, by that it was hye none.</l>
               <l>Earles and barons were soone set, and rich meate were foorth set.</l>
               <l>There lacked none certainely, of rich meate and minstrelsie.</l>
               <l>When it drew toward the night, a rich supper there was dight.</l>
               <l>And afterward verament, a knight and she to chamber went.</l>
               <l>Vpon her bed where she sat, the Earle came to hir with that.</l>
               <l>With barons a great company, with pye meate and with spicery.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:12215:27"/>
               <l>When they had dronken the wine, sir said Iosian and loue mine,</l>
               <l>Let no persone here be, this night to heare our priuitie,</l>
               <l>Neither knight maiden nor swayne, my selfe shalbe your chamberlayne.</l>
               <l>He said lemman it. shal be so, man and maide he made out go.</l>
               <l>He shut the doore well and fast, and set him downe at the last.</l>
               <l>To haue a curtaine it was law, before the bed he did it draw,</l>
               <l>Then on a girdell without leasing, she made a knot riding.</l>
               <l>About his necke she drewit thore, and strangled him without more.</l>
               <l>Then on a beame she hanged him hy, and let him hang for his folly.</l>
               <l>The night passed in that wise, the barons gan for to arise.</l>
               <l>Some on hunting &amp; some to the church, &amp; workmen rose to worke.</l>
               <l>The halfe day past without fayle, the barons had of him meruayle.</l>
               <l>Some said let him be still, of Iosian he hath his will.</l>
               <l>The midday when it drew to noone a baron spake then soone.</l>
               <l>I meruaile how may this bée, I will goe to the chamber and sée.</l>
               <l>He smote the doore then so fast, that all to péeces he it brast.</l>
               <l>Arise he said thou Earle Mile, for thou hast slept a great while.</l>
               <l>Thy head aketh I wote well, thou hast neede of a candell.</l>
               <l>Nay said she I vndertake, his head shall neuer more ake.</l>
               <l>I haue charmed him for that sore, that his head shall neuer ake more.</l>
               <l>Now I haue vnknit the wedding, younder mayst thou sée him hang.</l>
               <l>He shal neuer woman spill, do with me what so euer ye will.</l>
               <l>All they made great sorrow, the other day on the morrow.</l>
               <l>Se was dight verament, in a fire to be brent.</l>
               <l>Without the towne was set a stake, a great fire did they make.</l>
               <l>In a Castle lay Ascapart, and ouer the wal looked thetherward.</l>
               <l>And had great wonder truly, what that fire might signifie.</l>
               <l>He thought in his hart then, that Iosian some wo was in.</l>
               <l>Of the Castle where he was lockt, a touret he had all to broke.</l>
               <l>He was so wo and woode, that he lept into the floode.</l>
               <l>And fast by him also hote, came a Fysher with his bote.</l>
               <l>And Ascapart tooke the bote in hand, and rowed it vnto the land.</l>
               <l>Towards the foolke he gan looke, <hi>Beuis,</hi> came after and him ouertooke.</l>
               <l>And saide théefe where hast thou be, where is my quéene I left with thée,</l>
               <l>Sir <hi>Beuis</hi> Lord mercy he sayd, the Earle Mile hath me betrayd.</l>
               <l>Toward the fire they hyed them bliue, the preist than Iosian shriue.</l>
               <l>Christs blessing haue he among, for he taryed her so long.</l>
               <l>When the fire was all ready, in her smock she stood thereby.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:12215:28"/>
               <l>Right as they should hir bren, on Arundell Beuis gan ren,</l>
               <l>And in his hand good Morglay, and Ascapart went an other way.</l>
               <l>And all they about found, Beuis and he slew to the ground,</l>
               <l>There was neither knight ne swaine, that passed away vnslayne,</l>
               <l>And what made the false Earle Mile, for his treason and his gile,</l>
               <l>Beuis tooke with him than, both Ascapart and Iosian,</l>
               <l>And went foorth anone right, till they came to the yle of wight,</l>
               <l>Sir Sabere, welcomed with good hart, both Beuis, Iosian, and Ascapart.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How sir Beuis and sir Sabere his eame sent their messengers far and wide, for men of armes to succour them in that tide, against sir Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, that held Beuis heritage by treason, that was imagined by the wicked woman his mother, and how in the fielde Ascapart bare Sir Murdure and his horse, maugre of all his host into the castle, and how he was sodden to death in a Caudron.<figure/>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:28"/>
                  <l>SAbere and Beuis sent their sond, wide about in euery land,</l>
                  <l>After right great chiualry, of stalworth knights and hardy,</l>
                  <l>That they might finde them, yea, both stout and hardy men,</l>
                  <l>Spared they neither siluer nor gold, for the best men haue they would.</l>
                  <l>Beuis was curteise and frée, to euery man in his degrée,</l>
                  <l>There came Earles and barons iwis, for to succour sir Beuis,</l>
                  <l>There came knights squiers &amp; pages, each one had of him good wages,</l>
                  <l>And rich giftes more and lesse, each man after his doughtinesse,</l>
                  <l>Therefore each man to him sought, he tooke &amp; left what he best thought,</l>
                  <l>Euer he chase him of the best, that he could finde either east or west,</l>
                  <l>Sir Murdure much sorow made he, whē he saw Beuis had such a meny</l>
                  <l>The Countesse said dread ye nought, of good counsayle I am thought,</l>
                  <l>Ye shall send in certaine, after the power of Almaine,</l>
                  <l>Also you shall send your sond, after my father into Scotland,</l>
                  <l>He will come to you readely, with a full great company,</l>
                  <l>And we may haue many mo, out of England and wales also,</l>
                  <l>Wherfore should ye dread then, while ye may haue so many men,</l>
                  <l>If Beuis sée you haue this rout, he will flye away for doubt,</l>
                  <l>Sir Murdure did by her counsaile, the messenger went without faile,</l>
                  <l>That afterward without leasing, to Hampton came Prince and King,</l>
                  <l>There came with the king of Scotland, the number of seuen thousand,</l>
                  <l>There came out of Almaine, with sir Morys of Viane,</l>
                  <l>Sixty thousand with helmes bright, and well armed for to fight,</l>
                  <l>And sir Murdure had also, thrée thousand men and more,</l>
                  <l>Now lordings said sir Murdure, that hither come me to succour,</l>
                  <l>Often ye haue heard speake pardy, of the strife betwéene Sabere &amp; me,</l>
                  <l>Now to helpe him for to fight, beuis of Hampton a noble knight,</l>
                  <l>Well I thought he had béene dead, what is therefore best I read,</l>
                  <l>He threateneth me to be slayne, and that he will win his land agayne,</l>
                  <l>A Gyant with him he hath brought, an earthly man séemeth he nought,</l>
                  <l>Neither of flesh nor yet of fell, for he is lyke the Diuell of hell,</l>
                  <l>Men call him Ascapart throughout, of him forsooth I haue great doubt,</l>
                  <l>But Lordings he said arme you well, both of yron and eke of stéele,</l>
                  <l>Though Ascapart be stif and sterke, many hands make light worke,</l>
                  <l>When his hoast was armed and dight, they shiped to the yle of wight,</l>
                  <l>And all the yle was then bespred, with the power sir Murdure ledde,</l>
                  <l>Sir Sabere looked out at a tower, and saw the hoast of sir Murdure,</l>
                  <l>And all smartly downe gan he go, for to tell sir Beuis so,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:29"/>
                  <l>And saide <hi>Beuis</hi> now counsaile, I trow it would vs auayle.</l>
                  <l>In this Castle to hould vs still, and to defend vs from ill.</l>
                  <l>For such an hoast as hath Murdure, saw I neuer in any stour.</l>
                  <l>Do away Sabere sayd <hi>Beuis</hi> tho, for if they had as many mo.</l>
                  <l>Against vs they haue no might, they haue the wrong and we the right.</l>
                  <l>Arme you all <hi>Beuis</hi> gan cry, that we were armed hastely.</l>
                  <l>And ye shall haue sir Sabere, thrée thousand vnder your banner.</l>
                  <l>And I as many shall lead, of doughty men good at néede.</l>
                  <l>For I will haue the forward, and then he said to Ascapart.</l>
                  <l>Thou shalt dwell not for thy, with thrée thousand men hardy.</l>
                  <l>When we haue medled a stound, and each brought other to ground.</l>
                  <l>And that the stoure is most strong, hye the thether and dwell not long.</l>
                  <l>For thrée thousand of fresh men, good déedes shall they do then.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beuis</hi> then his horne did blow, for all men should him know.</l>
                  <l>By that blowing sir Murdure, knew they gathered the stoure.</l>
                  <l>He said lordings without fayle, now commeth our foe to battaile.</l>
                  <l>Be ye hardy and stout also, for we be as many mo.</l>
                  <l>Two battailes did they make, the king of Scotland one gan take.</l>
                  <l>Sir Murdure the other lad, either of them ten thousand had.</l>
                  <l>The first that of the castel came out, was sir <hi>Beuis</hi> with his rout.</l>
                  <l>And Sabere with his company, came after full boldly.</l>
                  <l>Either hoast gan other defy, and euery man to other ready.</l>
                  <l>Sir Morys of Viane, rode fast sir Sabere againe.</l>
                  <l>And Sabere met him ywis, and such a stroke he gaue Morys.</l>
                  <l>That quite away gan he cleaue, from the shoulder arme and sléeue.</l>
                  <l>Before the preace went sir <hi>Beuis,</hi> on euery side he slew iwis.</l>
                  <l>There might none him withstand, that saw the king of Scotland.</l>
                  <l>He pressed in with his rout, and beset <hi>Beuis</hi> round about.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beuis</hi> then began to play, and made roume with Morglay.</l>
                  <l>He would not stint then so, till he went the king to.</l>
                  <l>And such a stroke he him let, that horse and man to ground went.</l>
                  <l>But such succour came to him tho, at that time <hi>Beuis</hi> might not him slo.</l>
                  <l>But or he was horsed againe, an hundred men had <hi>Beuis</hi> slayne.</l>
                  <l>Foorth procéedeth <hi>Beuis</hi> in the throng, on euery side downe he slong.</l>
                  <l>He neuer stinted in that stoure, till he came to sir Murdure.</l>
                  <l>Traitour he said with great enuy, turne the now I thée defy.</l>
                  <l>When Murdure saw he was bested, he tourned his backe &amp; wold haue fled</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Beuis</hi> smot after w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> good Morglay, but fayled him there well away.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:29"/>
                  <l>For by his back the stroke fell downe, &amp; hit it vpon his saddel cropowne</l>
                  <l>And smote it asunder to the ground, horse and sadle both in that stound.</l>
                  <l>But there came hastely succour, and horsed againe sir Murdure.</l>
                  <l>And boldy then did he abide, the people dyed on euery side.</l>
                  <l>Beuis rode foorth on Arundell, on euery side he did them fell.</l>
                  <l>Some lay bléeding as a swine, and some began then to pine.</l>
                  <l>And some their visage did pare, that men might sée their téeth bare.</l>
                  <l>There went none vnmarkt away, that he might hit with Morglay.</l>
                  <l>For sore agrieued was he, where he had one they had thrée.</l>
                  <l>But Beuis and Sabere bare them so, against one they slew two.</l>
                  <l>When the throng was heard, than came foorth Ascapart.</l>
                  <l>All on foote I you swere, for there might no horse him beare.</l>
                  <l>He tooke his staffe in his hand, and slew downe all that he fand.</l>
                  <l>When Ascapart came with his rout, then had sir Murdure great doubt.</l>
                  <l>For he brought with him then, thrée thousand of fresh men.</l>
                  <l>And felled downe on euery side, and slew all that would abide.</l>
                  <l>Great pitie men might haue séene, of the murther that there hath béene.</l>
                  <l>Fearefull they were of Ascapart, for he smote so sore and hard.</l>
                  <l>That thrée thousand they might sée, flye and drowne them in the sea.</l>
                  <l>Beuis called Ascapart him till, and said fellow heare my skill.</l>
                  <l>Looke that thou take good héede, of him that rideth on the white stéede.</l>
                  <l>And beare him aliue vnto the tower, for that same is sir Murdure.</l>
                  <l>Yes said Ascapart tho, we shall shriue him or we go.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ascapart</hi> with his staffe, many their deaths wound he gaffe.</l>
                  <l>With great strength &amp; much payn, he came to sir Murdure of almaine.</l>
                  <l>And all on horse as he sat there, vnder his arme he gan him beare.</l>
                  <l>Than began Murdures men to hie, to rescue him he should not dye.</l>
                  <l>The king of Scotland with his rout, beset <hi>Ascapart</hi> round about.</l>
                  <l>And when sir Beuis and sir Sabere, came there with their power.</l>
                  <l>And slew all that would stand, to the number of thrée thousand.</l>
                  <l>And maugre if they had sworne, Murdure was to the castle borne.</l>
                  <l>The king of Scotland was then beset, whē he sawe Murdure to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> castle fet</l>
                  <l>And all his meny downe smite, he turned to his backe as lite.</l>
                  <l>Then they would no longer abide, but slew them downe on euery side.</l>
                  <l>Sir Beuis and sir Sabere, chased them with their power.</l>
                  <l>And fast followed he, and many fled into the sea.</l>
                  <l>And they that stoode him againe, they were all maimed and slaine.</l>
                  <l>Some their shanks by the knée, and some quartered in thrée.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:30"/>
                  <l>Some their nose and some their lip, the king of Scotland had a ship,</l>
                  <l>And fled away by the west, to the place that liked them best,</l>
                  <l>Beuis and Sabere turned againe, into the Castle glad and faine,</l>
                  <l>Sir <hi>Beuis</hi> without any let, made a caudron on the fire be set,</l>
                  <l>Full of pich and brimstone, a worse death was neuer none,</l>
                  <l>When the caudron boyled hard, Murdure was cast into the midward,</l>
                  <l>That death dyed he sekerly, for the death of good sir Guy,</l>
                  <l>Thereof heard the Countesse, that sir Murdure dead was,</l>
                  <l>she stood aboue in a toure, so wo she was for sir Murdure,</l>
                  <l>she threw hir selfe downe &amp; broke hir neck, I beshrew y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> therfore doth reck</l>
                  <l>When sir <hi>Beuis</hi> tidings heard, of his mother how she farde,</l>
                  <l>As sory was he for her, as he was for his stepfather,</l>
                  <l>Soone after sir <hi>Beuis,</hi> Come to Southhampton is,</l>
                  <l>To take possession of his landes, that had béene long out of his hands,</l>
                  <l>The burgesses with much pride, against sir <hi>Beuis</hi> gan they ride,</l>
                  <l>And brought sir <hi>Beuis</hi> fayre and well, to Hampton to his owne Castell</l>
                  <l>Of Hampton all the baronage, came and did <hi>Beuis</hi> homage,</l>
                  <l>Then was <hi>Beuis</hi> glad and faine, that he had his enemies slayne,</l>
                  <l>Sent after the bishop of Colaine, than <hi>Beuis</hi> the sooth to sayne,</l>
                  <l>That he would for any thing, to be at his wedding,</l>
                  <l>When he was there come, two knightes had Iosian anone,</l>
                  <l>To church than they hir led, the bishop himselfe on the booke red,</l>
                  <l>And vnto <hi>Beuis</hi> was wedded bliue, to the ending of their liue,</l>
                  <l>Now hath <hi>Beuis</hi> recouered his state, two children by her he gat,</l>
                  <l>The first night together in feare, as you shall afterward heare,</l>
                  <l>Sabere counsailed him there, to go to London to king Edgare,</l>
                  <l>To make him homage as reason would, for his lands to chaleng &amp; hold,</l>
                  <l>Sir Beuis did after counsayling, and went foorth before the king,</l>
                  <l>And profered that king to do him homage, as it fell to his heritage,</l>
                  <l>King Edgare he asked what he hight, and what he claimed for his right,</l>
                  <l>Sir he said my name is Beuis, the Earledome of southhampton it is,</l>
                  <l>After my father sir Guy, that was slyne for his Lady,</l>
                  <l>With sir Murdure of Almaine, and thanked be God he is slaine,</l>
                  <l>Beuis said the king I hold me paid, I graunt that thou hast said,</l>
                  <l>His marshall tooke the king in hand, and said deliuer me thy wand,</l>
                  <l>For sir Guy his father was my marshal, and sir Beuis his sonne he shal</l>
                  <l>The yard to Beuis the king taketh, and his marshall him maketh,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>¶ Beuis is now of great might, beloued both of king and knight,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:30"/>
                  <l>Each man both Earle and Baron, loued and dread Beuis of Hampton.</l>
                  <l>For largely would he spend, and giftes both giue and send,</l>
                  <l>To euery man after his estate, no man had cause him to hate.</l>
                  <l>He was so curteous and so kinde, that euery man was his friend.</l>
                  <l>Saue sir Bryan of Cornwayle, he hated Beuis without fayle.</l>
                  <l>For Beuis had these offices, that sometime were his.</l>
                  <l>In the Somer at Whitsontide, when knightes doe on horsebacke ride.</l>
                  <l>A course they made vppon a day, stéedes and palfrayes to assay.</l>
                  <l>Which horse that best may runne, thrée mile the course was then.</l>
                  <l>He that best ride could, should haue fortie pound of gold.</l>
                  <l>Sir Beuis was appayed well, for much he trusted in Arundell.</l>
                  <l>On the morow when it was light, thither came both Baron and Knight.</l>
                  <l>With faire stéedes and much pride, that in that course would ride.</l>
                  <l>Two knightes were stolne before, a large halfe mile and more.</l>
                  <l>That none of his fellowes wote, Beuis with the spurres smote.</l>
                  <l>On Arundell so sayth the booke, and amid the way them ouertooke.</l>
                  <l>He had ridden the course in a while, or they though he had rid a mile.</l>
                  <l>Now hath Beuis the price woon, through Arundell that well did runne.</l>
                  <l>Wherefore with that and other cattell, he made the castle of Arundell.</l>
                  <l>The horse was praised in that case, for both swift and lusty he was.</l>
                  <l>The kinges sonne and his heire, thought the horse good and fayre.</l>
                  <l>And to Beuis then he hyed, and prayed him to haue his stéede.</l>
                  <l>No sayd Beuis for no gold, but aske me else what you would,</l>
                  <l>At your will you shall it haue, but Arundell do you not craue.</l>
                  <l>For any prayer you may pray, will I giue my stéede away.</l>
                  <l>The kinges sonne when he it saw, that his minde he could not draw.</l>
                  <l>Without any more fable, he went vnto sir Beuis stable.</l>
                  <l>For he would the horse vntye, but when he came somewhat nye.</l>
                  <l>That Arundell also hote, with his hinder foot he smote,</l>
                  <l>That he droue out his brayne, so he lay there dead slayne.</l>
                  <l>There was dole and much wéeping, when tydinges came to the king.</l>
                  <l>Foortwith the king verament, made to be set his Parliament.</l>
                  <l>And began for to ordayne, that sir Beuis should be slayne.</l>
                  <l>And be drawne with wilde beastes, his Barons would not his heastes.</l>
                  <l>They sayd that it were no skill, but Arundell should be at his will.</l>
                  <l>For he slew thy sonne so, but nought to Beuis may we doe.</l>
                  <l>Nay sayd Beuis for no castell, would I let slay Arundell.</l>
                  <l>For he is good euery where, yet had I rather the land forsweare.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:31"/>
                  <l>Then sir Brian of Cornewell said, sir this is my counsell.</l>
                  <l>That ye doe one of the two, I assent said <hi>Beuis</hi> tho.</l>
                  <l>Before you all I giue héere, mine heritage to Sabere.</l>
                  <l>Sir <hi>Beuis</hi> deliuered vp the wand, and there he forswore England.</l>
                  <l>A fortnight had he respite, for to wend all in delight.</l>
                  <l>And he after might be found, he should be taken and fast bound.</l>
                  <l>On this maner they were at one, and to Hampton he rode anone.</l>
                  <l>And together told he thore, of the case both lesse and more,</l>
                  <l>It is no longer but to morne, for we may not héere soiourne.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beuis</hi> and Iosian made all ready, and took their leaue for to ferry.</l>
                  <l>Saberes sonne that hight Terry, <hi>Beuis</hi> tooke with him for company.</l>
                  <l>Ascapart that false théefe, and for him he had much griefe.</l>
                  <l>He thought héere I do dwell, and get nothing but great trauell.</l>
                  <l>But if I might by Termagaunt, bring Iosian to Mambrant.</l>
                  <l>I should be welcome the king till, and haue a inough at my will.</l>
                  <l>This Ascapart false was he, for <hi>Beuis</hi> was falne in pouertie.</l>
                  <l>When a man is in pouertie fall, few friendes méeteth he with all.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Beuis and faire Iosian tooke their way into a straunge land, and how she trauailed in a Forest, and was delyuered of two children. And how Ascapart that false Fellon after his deliueraunce, came and bare her away, and after that how Beuis came to a great Iusting and Turnament and won the price.<figure/>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:31"/>
                  <l>NOw <hi>Beuis</hi> and Iosian foorth gan ride, till they came to a forrest side.</l>
                  <l>And Iosian that was so milde, in that wood trauailed with childe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beuis</hi> &amp; Tarry downe gan light, &amp; with their swords a lodge they dight.</l>
                  <l>And brought Iosian therein, for they could no better ginne.</l>
                  <l>Sir <hi>Beuis</hi> gan her seruice bed, for to helpe her at her néede.</l>
                  <l>She thanked him and said nay, for Gods loue go hence away.</l>
                  <l>Go and play you with Terry, and let me worke &amp; our Lady.</l>
                  <l>shall neuer womans priuitie, to man be shewed for me.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beuis</hi> and Terry went foorth there, for they would not per paines heare.</l>
                  <l>And Ascapart tooke another way, on reason thought these aye.</l>
                  <l>After that <hi>Beuis</hi> was gone her fro, she was deliuered of children two.</l>
                  <l>When Ascapart heard that case, that Iosian deliuered was.</l>
                  <l>To the lodge he went there, and Iosian away did beare.</l>
                  <l>There might no prayers her borow, I wonder her hart burst not for sorow</l>
                  <l>For he swore by Termagant, he would her lead to Mambrant.</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Beuis</hi> had heere long taryed, againe to the Lodge he him hied.</l>
                  <l>In the lodge found he no mo, but young small children two.</l>
                  <l>Than wist he not what to say, whan he saw Iosian was away.</l>
                  <l>Alas then said <hi>Beuis,</hi> Ascapart hath done treason ywis.</l>
                  <l>Sir Beuis fell downe in a traunce, and sir Terry did him vphaunce.</l>
                  <l>When Beuis saw no better would be, his rich mantle then tooke he.</l>
                  <l>and lapped the two children therein, for they were some deale of his kin.</l>
                  <l>No longer then would he abide, he tooke his children &amp; foorth gan ride,</l>
                  <l>A foster in the wood he met, sir Beuis him asked and faire him gréet.</l>
                  <l>Fellow said Beuis than, sawest thou ought of such a man.</l>
                  <l>Lead a woman by any way, sir said the fosser nay.</l>
                  <l>What manner of man art thou bacheler, sir he saide I am a foster.</l>
                  <l>Wilt thou said Beuis so Christ thée shield, do christe héere an hethē child</l>
                  <l>But right now was it borne, full early it hath the mother lorne.</l>
                  <l>And kéepe it but this seauen yéere, for ten marke haue if héere.</l>
                  <l>Gladly saide the foster tho, he tooke the child and the siluer also.</l>
                  <l>And said what shall I call him sir knight, Guy he said as my father hight</l>
                  <l>And when it is seuen yéere, of each land do thou enquire.</l>
                  <l>After Beuis of Hampton, my name is so by my crowne.</l>
                  <l>And bring the child to me, and well rewarded shalt thou be.</l>
                  <l>Gladly sir he said ywis, he went his waies and Beuis his.</l>
                  <l>Foorh they rod so saith the booke, and an other man they ouertooke.</l>
                  <l>And asked what man was he, he said a fisher of the sea.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:32"/>
                  <l>And <hi>Beuis</hi> with good semblaunt made with him the same couenaunt.</l>
                  <l>That he should on this manner, his other sonne to kepe this vii. yeare.</l>
                  <l>The fisher graunted as <hi>Beuis</hi> sayd, he tooke the childe and held him payde.</l>
                  <l>After himselfe in that while, he christened the childe, and hight him Myle.</l>
                  <l>Foorth rode <hi>Beuis</hi> by dale and downe, till they came to Castle towne.</l>
                  <l>He tooke his Inne as a curteous knight, and fast to supper he him dight.</l>
                  <l>At a window <hi>Beuis</hi> looked out, he saw in the stréetes all about.</l>
                  <l>Stéedes trapped faire and bright, Dukes and Earles, and many a knight</l>
                  <l>Out of the windowes on euery syde, armes were hanged fayre &amp; wyde.</l>
                  <l>Haroldes gan the armes soone discrye, and therof <hi>Beuis</hi> meruailed greatly.</l>
                  <l>And asked his hoast thereof tyding, sir he said heard ye nothing,</l>
                  <l>Of the great iusting that shall be, to morow in this Citie?</l>
                  <l>The Dukes daughter and his heire, she is maiden good and fayre.</l>
                  <l>Her father is now néere dead, therefore it is giuen her to rede.</l>
                  <l>A great Iusting for to trye, that he that hath the maistery,</l>
                  <l>Shall this mayt haue to wed, and her land to guyd and led.</l>
                  <l>Now sayd <hi>Beuis</hi> to Terry, shall we iust for that Lady?</l>
                  <l>Yes said Terry God forbid else, if it were sooth as he vs telles.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beuis</hi> gaue the man for his tyding, of grotes twentie shilling.</l>
                  <l>On y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> morow whē it was day light, then rose both baron, squire, &amp; knight.</l>
                  <l>Faire tokens they gan on them throw, wherby y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Lady should thē know.</l>
                  <l>Sir <hi>Beuis</hi> and sir Terry, armed themselues full hastily.</l>
                  <l>Sir <hi>Beuis</hi> bare colours of paiment, a red Lyon of gold rampant.</l>
                  <l>And foorth rode Terry and hée, to the iusting where it should bée.</l>
                  <l>The faire Lady Elinoure, ouer the castle lay that houre.</l>
                  <l>And the Iusting shée beheld, what knight did best in the field.</l>
                  <l>Then the knightes began to ride, each to other on euery side.</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Beuis</hi> rode first againe, the Emperours sonne of Almayne.</l>
                  <l>To him <hi>Beuis</hi> bare so fast, that horse and man to ground he cast.</l>
                  <l>The Erle of Florence stoutly than, against Beuis in hast ranne.</l>
                  <l>And Beuis met him in the field, and hit him amiddes the shield.</l>
                  <l>That two yardes brode and more, he cast him from his horse thore.</l>
                  <l>Then came foorth Duke Antony, who was Duke of Burgony.</l>
                  <l>He was strong and of great price, and thus he said to sir Beuis.</l>
                  <l>Turne thée here and make defence, I will auenge the Earle Florence,</l>
                  <l>Then Beuis would no longer abide, but smote Arundell vnder the side.</l>
                  <l>Each to other then droue, that their shaftes all to roue.</l>
                  <l>But sir Beuis so hard him thrust, that his shoulder bone all to brust.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:32"/>
                  <l>Therefore he was agrieued sore, for that day he might iust no more.</l>
                  <l>And then rode foorth sir Terry, to the kinges brother of Hungary.</l>
                  <l>And gaue him such a rebowne, that horse and man fell downe.</l>
                  <l>Then came the Earle Hamant, and to Terry made assent.</l>
                  <l>Terry hit him amiddes the shield, and bare him quite into the field.</l>
                  <l>There was no knight redily, that might sir Beuis and Terry.</l>
                  <l>Full narrowly the other sought, but sir <hi>Beuis</hi> spared them nought.</l>
                  <l>The steward of the same land, sir Beuis cast on the sand.</l>
                  <l>And that reioyst faire Elinore, for the boast he made before.</l>
                  <l>And many Beuis bare throughout, so that they stood in great doubt.</l>
                  <l>They stinted not till it was night, that they wanted the day light.</l>
                  <l>Then they ceased their playing, on the morow they heard tiding,</l>
                  <l>That all the praise and renowne, was giuen to Beuis of Hampton.</l>
                  <l>Dame Elinor would not blinne, till Beuis came to hir Inne.</l>
                  <l>She said sir by my counsaile, you shall me wedde without faile.</l>
                  <l>Each to other for terme of life. Nay sayd Beuis I haue a wife.</l>
                  <l>He told how she was taken away, thorow treason I you say,</l>
                  <l>And for her he was full woe: now she said sith it is so.</l>
                  <l>You shall all this seauen yeare, be my Lord in cleane manner.</l>
                  <l>And if you finde her not by than, I will thée haue before any man.</l>
                  <l>And the next to thée truely, is the good knight sir Terry.</l>
                  <l>And if this may stand me in stéede, I graunt said Beuis to this déede.</l>
                  <l>And thus was he her gouernour, and led the land in great honour.</l>
                  <l>As Sabere slept all night in bed, he thought of Beuis that was bestéed.</l>
                  <l>Through Ascapart his swaine, and how he had sir Beuis slaine.</l>
                  <l>When he waked his hart was cold, his dreame to his wife he tolde.</l>
                  <l>Sir she said as I wéene, Beuis is brought into some téene.</l>
                  <l>For as I trow by my life, he hath lost childe and wife.</l>
                  <l>Through Ascapart that false théefe, Beuis is in some griefe.</l>
                  <l>I shall them séeke said Sabere, twelue knightes he did attire,</l>
                  <l>In Palmers wéede by saint Iohn, well armed euery one.</l>
                  <l>All armed sure and well, both of Iron and stéele.</l>
                  <l>Foorth they went more and lesse, till they came to heathenesse.</l>
                  <l>When Iosian was nigh Mambrant, Iesu Christ be hir warrant.</l>
                  <l>She met Sabere in the visage, and said Palmer in her language,</l>
                  <l>I pray you of succour and read, vnlesse you helpe I am but dead.</l>
                  <l>Certes Iosian said Sabere, it liketh me that you be here.</l>
                  <l>For of you Madame verament, I shall make Beuis a present.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:33"/>
                  <l>He was a gréeued with Ascapart, and assailed him full hard.</l>
                  <l>They him beset on euery side, but none would his dints abide.</l>
                  <l>From his strokes they did shonne, and start againe as knights anone.</l>
                  <l>He had great strokes and sore, as one was héere and the other thore.</l>
                  <l>And as he smote after a knight, Sabere ran to him full right.</l>
                  <l>And with a sword without doubt, he bare Ascapart throughout.</l>
                  <l>And he fell dead to the ground, glad was Iosian in that flound.</l>
                  <l>Sir Sabere tooke Iosian than, that was as white as any Swan.</l>
                  <l>Her body that was faire and gent, he noynted with an oyntment.</l>
                  <l>And made her yelow and greene, that before was faire and shéene.</l>
                  <l>That no man should her know, therefore he discoulered her so.</l>
                  <l>And sithen Beuis they sought, but tidings of him found they nought.</l>
                  <l>That wilbe found, found shalbe, on a day they went through the Citie.</l>
                  <l>And led Iosian to her Inne, and he went foorth some meate to win<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Saber went to the Castle gate, and met his sonne Terry there at<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>He prayed him in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> honer of the roode, that he would giue him some good.</l>
                  <l>Terry beheld him as bliue, and said Palmer so may I thriue.</l>
                  <l>There shall no meat be for thée to déere, for thou art like my father fabere</l>
                  <l>Sabere said he, by Gods grace, so my mother said I was.</l>
                  <l>When Terry saw that it was hée, he ranne to him with heart frée.</l>
                  <l>And kissed him and asked father, what made him to come thether.</l>
                  <l>Sabere said sonne thou shalt sée, what thing I haue brought with mée.</l>
                  <l>Foorth they went together in feare, till they came to the Inne of Sabere.</l>
                  <l>Then Sabere and Terry with good intent, washed away the oyntment.</l>
                  <l>Faire and well they her dight, and brought her to the Castle right.</l>
                  <l>And tooke her than to Beuis in hond, there came neuer to thē such a sond.</l>
                  <l>Ther came the Fisher and the Foster, with two children cléere.</l>
                  <l>For they held Beuis couenant right, he made each of them a knight,</l>
                  <l>And than wedded for sir Terry, of that land the faire Ladie.</l>
                  <l>There was a rich feast ywisse, on euery side ioy and blisse.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>THis beginneth a new tiding, of king Iour and Ermine king.</l>
                  <l>Betwéene them gan battaile make, and all was for Iosians sake.</l>
                  <l>A Palmer told Beuis thereof tiding, and sir Beuis all hying.</l>
                  <l>Sent after great chiualrie, of doughtie knights and hardie.</l>
                  <l>That he had not knowne before, and all they to him swore.</l>
                  <l>When Beuis gathered his company, he tooke his leaue of sir Terry.</l>
                  <l>And Terry profered with him for to goe, but Beuis said it should not so.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:33"/>
                  <l>Sabere thy father shal wend with me, If I haue néede I shal send to thée.</l>
                  <l>Guy and Miles to horse gan dight, with stalworth swordes for to fight.</l>
                  <l>And Beuis with all his company, went foorth to Armony.</l>
                  <l>Of his comming the king was blith, and cryed mercy an hundreth sith.</l>
                  <l>And said if thou wilt forgiue mée, I wilbe Christened for loue of thée.</l>
                  <l>On that couenant he gaue him a kisse, that they be accorded ywis.</l>
                  <l>Without any other dome, Beuis then sent for the bishop of Rome.</l>
                  <l>That he should send his clarkes good, Sabere them bishopped or they yood</l>
                  <l>That they might with cléere clargie, Christen the land of Armony.</l>
                  <l>For the kings graunt they had, the bishop it heard and he was glad.</l>
                  <l>And hath sent after his saw, clearkes that were wise in the law.</l>
                  <l>They christened Ermine with their hand, &amp; sithen all the people of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> land</l>
                  <l>In many a place Beuis gan worch, Abbies and many a good Church.</l>
                  <l>So was the land of Armony, through Beuis christened truely,</l>
                  <l>King Iour heard of that sand, that Beuis was come to land.</l>
                  <l>A great hoast made he tho, fortie thousands Sarasins and mo.</l>
                  <l>And to Armony went he then, and there began to robbe and brenne.</l>
                  <l>When Beuis heard that he was come, a great host they did them anone.</l>
                  <l>And rode king Iour againe, with all his power might and maine.</l>
                  <l>It was a faire fight to them y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> beheld, when both parties met in the field.</l>
                  <l>The field shone wondrous bright, with bassenets that were light.</l>
                  <l>But soone after they were other, when both the hosts were together.</l>
                  <l>On both parts the Romains saies, they shot arrowes with bow turkais.</l>
                  <l>Quarrels with alblasters &amp; cast stones, ther was a dolful sight for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> nones</l>
                  <l>For arrowes were ther great plentie, there might not one hoast an other sée</l>
                  <l>With swords bright that well can byte, each man gan other smite.</l>
                  <l>But when they handled both the same, there was earnest and no game.</l>
                  <l>And Beuis with Morglay stirred so, that all he hit he smote in two.</l>
                  <l>The Sarasins gan Beuis to defie, and came thick about him redely.</l>
                  <l>Therewith he was well apayed &amp; lough, on euery side he downe thē slough</l>
                  <l>So many he slew in that fight, to his stirrop they lay vpright.</l>
                  <l>He rode foorth when he them left, and there he slew as many eft.</l>
                  <l>Sabere his came though he were old, he shewed y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he was strong &amp; bold.</l>
                  <l>He slew before him ten and twelue, till he came to the king himselfe.</l>
                  <l>And then Maugre of Mahound, he bare the king downe.</l>
                  <l>Then Sarasins folowed on a heap, to king Iour gan they leap.</l>
                  <l>And with force horsed him againe, and all at once on Sabere they laine.</l>
                  <l>Beuis saw Sabere was in doubt, and pressed foorth among the rout.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:34"/>
                  <l>And rescued him in that stour, and himselfe went to king Iour.</l>
                  <l>And led him foorth all with force, and betooke sir Sabere his horse,</l>
                  <l>Into the tower they did him bring, and presented Iour vnto the king.</l>
                  <l>Sabere led him all quicke, the Sarasines followed full thicke.</l>
                  <l>But such strokes gaue sir Beuis, that king Iour away led is.</l>
                  <l>For any thing they might doe, and when they saw that it was so,</l>
                  <l>They would no longer there abyde, Beuis and his men did after ride.</l>
                  <l>And made on them so hard a chase, that ten thousand slayne there was.</l>
                  <l>Many a knight in that field, were séene dead vnder their shield,</l>
                  <l>And many a Sarasine that day, with deathes woundes went away.</l>
                  <l>Many steedes men might sée, without maisters away flée.</l>
                  <l>And Sarasines men might heare, curse Mahound they had such feare.</l>
                  <l>When they had made that chase, they returned with great felace.</l>
                  <l>And sir Beuis right anone, made cast king Iour in prison.</l>
                  <l>Then king Iour sir Beuis prayed, that his raunsome might be payde.</l>
                  <l>And for a raunsome giue he wold, twentie tunnes of redde golde.</l>
                  <l>And thrée hundreth heads of silke, as many stéedes white as milke.</l>
                  <l>An hundred cuppes of gold fine, and as many of Musculine.</l>
                  <l>All this raunsome I shall thée giue, if thou now wilt let me liue.</l>
                  <l>Let thy seruant it bring, and I shall saue thy life sir king.</l>
                  <l>For so much I dread not thée, but for this treasure thou shalt goe frée.</l>
                  <l>Then was king Iour faine, for it to send his chamberlayne.</l>
                  <l>And he brought it without delay, and for his king he did it pay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>OF king Iour let we be, and of king Ermine speake we,</l>
                  <l>That should passe out of this life, and sent after his sonne blyue.</l>
                  <l>For Guy was Beuis eldest sonne, vpon his head he set the crowne.</l>
                  <l>And made him king of Armony, and soone after hastily,</l>
                  <l>Dyed king Ermine the hend, to heauen might his soule wend.</l>
                  <l>Vnto sir Beuis came Sabere, and tooke his leaue home to fare.</l>
                  <l>To England wonly he goe bliue, to his children and his wife.</l>
                  <l>Beuis bad him tarry verament, Sabere would not but home went.</l>
                  <l>Now is king Iour in Mambrant, and doth sweare by Termagant,</l>
                  <l>That he would him well aduaunce, that might steale by any chaunce.</l>
                  <l>Good Arundell with some treason, from sir Beuis of Southhampton.</l>
                  <l>And he might Arundell steale, I trow men might with him deale,</l>
                  <l>There was a théefe hight Robian, a quaint knaue and a foule felon.</l>
                  <l>He tooke on him the maystry, and went foorth to Armony.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:34"/>
                  <l>With his charmes and his craft, of Arundell <hi>Beuis</hi> he beraft.</l>
                  <l>And brought him into the towre, and presented him to king Iour.</l>
                  <l>Then was he well apayed, that <hi>Beuis</hi> was so betrayed.</l>
                  <l>Wo was <hi>Beuis</hi> the sooth to say, when he missed Arundell away.</l>
                  <l>As Sabere slept at night tide, he thought he saw Beuis ride.</l>
                  <l>And Arundell downe him cast, that two of his ribbes there brast.</l>
                  <l>When he waked he was afrayed, vnto his wife the dreame he said.</l>
                  <l>Sir said she ye doe wrong, ye dwell from <hi>Beuis</hi> all to long.</l>
                  <l>By him that was of Mary borne, I trow he hath his horse forlorne.</l>
                  <l>Then Sabere for sir <hi>Beuis</hi> sake, burdon and scrip gan to take.</l>
                  <l>He went foorth with good semblant, vntill he came to Mambrant.</l>
                  <l>Thether he went for to spye, and left the land of Armony.</l>
                  <l>Sir Sabere came by a riuer, where men did beasts water.</l>
                  <l>Where he saw as he abod, on Arundell how Robyan rode.</l>
                  <l>Sabere said by heauen king, true is now my dreaming.</l>
                  <l>Felow he said so Christ mée réede, this may be called a stéede.</l>
                  <l>He is brested without doubt, good fellow tourne thée about.</l>
                  <l>And as he tourned him there, vp behind lept sir Sabere.</l>
                  <l>And slew the théefe Robyan, with the ende of his tronchone.</l>
                  <l>He would no longer there abide, the Sarasins to the court gan ride.</l>
                  <l>And to the king they did tell, how one had gotten Arundell.</l>
                  <l>Then rose the cry in the Cittie, that they should after them hie.</l>
                  <l>They rode after fast in band, to the number of thrée thousand.</l>
                  <l>And full narrowly him beset, Iosian stoode in a turet.</l>
                  <l>All the folke beheld she well, and one riding on Arundell.</l>
                  <l>Vnto the hall she hyed her downe, and said sir without the towne.</l>
                  <l>Commeth one riding on your stéede, and surely he is in great dread.</l>
                  <l>He is beset without doubt, with men of armes a great rout.</l>
                  <l>Iesu said Beuis a while him saue, and succour should he soone haue.</l>
                  <l>First on horse was sir Guy, his brother Miles and sir Terry.</l>
                  <l>And sir <hi>Beuis</hi> fast hied he, with all knights of that Citie.</l>
                  <l>He hied him fast in that stoure, and brought Sabere good succour.</l>
                  <l>And slew the Sarasins downe right, that none of them scape might.</l>
                  <l>Good game had Sabere to be séene, how they lay sprawling on the gréene.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>TIdings came to king Iour, that his men were slaine in stoure.</l>
                  <l>He made to send hastely, after his brother king of Surry.</l>
                  <l>And told him how his men were dead, and asked him counsell &amp; rad.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:35"/>
                  <l>I shall thée say quod Bradwin, thou art holden a noble Sarafin.</l>
                  <l>In Pauy or in heathinnsse, is none to thée of doughtines.</l>
                  <l>Therefore I counsaile you so, ye do the battaile betwéene you two.</l>
                  <l>And make ready my fauchowne, and make my sacrifice to Mahoune.</l>
                  <l>That he send thée ouer hand, and forsooth I vnderstand.</l>
                  <l>That thou wilt a conquerour bée, and we will wend all with thée.</l>
                  <l>And stand with thee we will the while, and helpe thée in thy perill.</l>
                  <l>Now said king Iour I assent, and then smartly foorth they went.</l>
                  <l>And made Mahound sacrifice, with all the Sarasins that were wise.</l>
                  <l>And they prayed withouten mis, their king might be saued from Beuis.</l>
                  <l>When the king had so done, to arme him he went full soone.</l>
                  <l>And went foorth to armony, with thrée thousand men hardy.</l>
                  <l>Soone had Beuis tidings then, of king Iour and his men.</l>
                  <l>He tooke with him his sonnes two, Sabere and Terry and other mo.</l>
                  <l>And rode king Iour again, when Iour saw Beuis he was faine.</l>
                  <l>And said to Beuis I vnderstand, why ye be come into this land.</l>
                  <l>First he rauished me of my wife, and since bereft my men their life.</l>
                  <l>Therefore haue I taken counsaile, betwéene vs bold tattaile.</l>
                  <l>If thou me slay by Termagant, I graunt to thée the land of Mambrant</l>
                  <l>And if I thée slay not for thy, wilt thou graunt me Armony.</l>
                  <l>Beuis graunted as he had told, and vndertooke the battaile bold.</l>
                  <l>Into a place gan they ryde, enclosed with water on euery side.</l>
                  <l>They drew their swords hastely, and smote together with great enuie.</l>
                  <l>Their shields were brused y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> they bare, their helmes crased their browes tare</l>
                  <l>Together they went another way, &amp; <hi>Beuis</hi> hit Iour with Morglay.</l>
                  <l>That his helme gan downe pare, there men might sée his head bare.</l>
                  <l>And a quarter of his shield, fell downe in the field.</l>
                  <l>Horse and man he downe gan driue, and fell to the ground that bliue.</l>
                  <l>Vp lept king Iour and stoode, and cryed on Mahound as he were woode.</l>
                  <l>And smote at Beuis with a fauchowne, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
                     <hi>Beuis</hi> of Arundel lighted downe</l>
                  <l>And right as <hi>Beuis</hi> downe lighting, Iour him smote without leysing.</l>
                  <l>Aboue sir <hi>Beuis</hi> helme on hye, that the crest downe gan flye.</l>
                  <l>And brused the helme in sunder, sir Beuis knéeled and that was wonder</l>
                  <l>Sir Beuis than was grieued sore, vp he lept without any more.</l>
                  <l>And gaue king Iour such a clout, he neuer rose after without doubt,</l>
                  <l>The Sarasins were wo y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> stond, when they saw Iour dead on y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ground.</l>
                  <l>That he should neuer rise nor go, therefore they were full sory and wo.</l>
                  <l>The other people would haue fled, but Guy and Miles in that stéed.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:35"/>
                  <l>Slew them more and lesse, or they might the water passe.</l>
                  <l>And some they drencht in that flood, there was none quicke againe yood.</l>
                  <l>Sir <hi>Beuis</hi> of purueiaunce, he tooke king Iours countenaunce.</l>
                  <l>And made them it on them throw, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> no man might from Iour him know</l>
                  <l>A greater power with him too, and went to Mambraunt that Cittie.</l>
                  <l>When they within the towre, saw the comming of king Ioure.</l>
                  <l>All they were glad and faine, and opened the gates againe.</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Beuis</hi> to the citie gan ride, with great ioy and much pride.</l>
                  <l>And through that quint gin, that rich citie gan they win.</l>
                  <l>And made them all become his men, and did him homage then.</l>
                  <l>And they cursed their Mawmetrie, and beleued in God and our Lady.</l>
                  <l>And who that would not do so, immediately he did him slo.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>NOw is <hi>Beuis</hi> king of that land, that sometime king Iour had in hand</l>
                  <l>Iosian that was bright &amp; shéene, twise thereof she hath ben Quéene</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beuis</hi> and Sabere vppon a day, with haukes and hounds went to play.</l>
                  <l>As they came by a riuer, soone they met a messenger.</l>
                  <l>He asked them after a knight, that sir Saber was by right.</l>
                  <l>Anon sir Sabere gan foorth spring, and said messenger what tiding.</l>
                  <l>Sir he said Edgar our king, through his stewards counsailing.</l>
                  <l>He hath disherited thine heire, certes said Sabere that is not faire.</l>
                  <l>He rode to <hi>Beuis</hi> and said tho, and asked him leaue for to go.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beuis</hi> said vnto sir Sabere, I will also goe thether.</l>
                  <l>With Iosian, Miles and sir Guy, and thy sonne sir Terry.</l>
                  <l>Thereof was sir Sabere glad, for great power with him he had.</l>
                  <l>And so went foorth to England, with men of armes ten thousand.</l>
                  <l>And sailed to Southhampton, with many knights of renowne.</l>
                  <l>Saberes wife and Robert her heire, welcomed them all full faire.</l>
                  <l>And they did them to vnderstand, how all sir Sabers land.</l>
                  <l>The king arested without faile, through sir Brians counsaile,</l>
                  <l>Who saith he may take them away, for <hi>Arundell</hi> his sonne did slay.</l>
                  <l>Then said <hi>Beuis</hi> by God on liue, we will hie thether bliue.</l>
                  <l>Beuis rode foorth with little boast, at Putneth he felt his hoast.</l>
                  <l>It is from London miles thrée, where he left his company.</l>
                  <l>And rode himselfe to London, saue twelue knights all alone.</l>
                  <l>Then he went to king Edgar, and asked him in what manner.</l>
                  <l>He had disherited sir Sabere, and his sonne that was his heire.</l>
                  <l>I deliuered him mine heritage, héere before your baronage.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:36"/>
                  <l>The king said to him right soone, sir Beuis if ought be misdoone.</l>
                  <l>It shalbe mended in a parliament, with Earles and barons assent.</l>
                  <l>All the knights that were there, to sir <hi>Beuis</hi> made good chéere.</l>
                  <l>Saue sir Brian, foule him be fall, he was his most foe of all</l>
                  <l>Sir said Brian to the king, is not this a wondrous thing.</l>
                  <l>That this for banished swaine, is come into England againe.</l>
                  <l>Ye ought him to hand and draw, as a traitour against the law.</l>
                  <l>The king would pardon sir <hi>Beuis,</hi> but the Steward against it is.</l>
                  <l>Beuis was both wroth and wood, &amp; aunswered neither ill nor good.</l>
                  <l>He tooke his lodging in the towne, and at his meat sate him downe.</l>
                  <l>Then sir Briant foorth went he, and made a cry through the citie.</l>
                  <l>All those that armes might beare, and fight with shield and speare.</l>
                  <l>That they should arme them anone, to auenge the kings sonne.</l>
                  <l>Then were the gates lockt, windowes and dores fast stopt,</l>
                  <l>Chaines drawen in euery stréete, to let sir Beuis you may wéete.</l>
                  <l>When Beuis heard that treason, vp he lept as a Lyon.</l>
                  <l>Full soone he earmed him tho, and bad his men for to goe.</l>
                  <l>Vnto Putneth some priuy way, and to my sonnes do ye say.</l>
                  <l>That they hie them hether bliue, if they will haue me on llue.</l>
                  <l>For whiles I fight héere without, ye may go void of doubt.</l>
                  <l>Beuis lept on Arundell, he had no longer time to dwell.</l>
                  <l>The first he met without fayle, was sir Bryan of Cornewayle.</l>
                  <l>He had with him a great rout, and beset Beuis round about.</l>
                  <l>And so sir Beuis said to Brian, turne thée as thou art a man.</l>
                  <l>Thou art an olde knight of warre, and to him he bare a speare.</l>
                  <l>So hard to Beuis he it droue, that the shield all to roue.</l>
                  <l>Then he houed and beheld, how the Steward broke the shéeld.</l>
                  <l>Now said Beuis will I smite, and began that déede to quite.</l>
                  <l>He smote Arundell vnder the side, and with Morglay in that tide.</l>
                  <l>He hit Bryan on the crowne, and to the saddle cloue him downe.</l>
                  <l>Beuis sterred him in that stound, two hundred he cast to ground.</l>
                  <l>He rode foorth into Broadstréete, many Lumberds did he méete.</l>
                  <l>And assailed Beuis wonders fast, on euery side he them downe cast.</l>
                  <l>Beuis had béene in many a land, and many battaile had in hand.</l>
                  <l>Yet he was neuer so woe a man, in any battaile as he was than.</l>
                  <l>But he defended him full well, and many of them he did fell.</l>
                  <l>On euery side downe he them cast, and did ride among them fast.</l>
                  <l>Till he came to the Cheape, where he found men on a heape.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:36"/>
                  <l>Then againe began the fight, betwéene the citie and the knight.</l>
                  <l>Beuis said that was so good, to the folke that there stood.</l>
                  <l>I réede that ye vnlock the gate, and let me scape out there at.</l>
                  <l>For if I dye héere within, little worship should you win.</l>
                  <l>All against him did they crye, yéelde thée Beuis or thou shalt dye.</l>
                  <l>Beuis fought as he were wood, and bathed Morglay in their blood.</l>
                  <l>sixe hundred men he cast to ground, and had neither wem nor wound.</l>
                  <l>But much blood of that man, through sweat of his body came.</l>
                  <l>Then it drew toward night, the people were still ready to fight.</l>
                  <l>Then began Arundell his stéede, to help sir Beuis at his néede.</l>
                  <l>by twentie foote on euery side, durst no man that horse abyde.</l>
                  <l>And so lasted than that fight, betwene them all a somers night.</l>
                  <l>Sir Beuis knights I vnderstand, to Putneth brought their sond.</l>
                  <l>That Beuis sons shuld by thē bliue, if they wold haue their father a liue.</l>
                  <l>When Iosian heard them speake of Beuis, in a sowne fallen she is.</l>
                  <l>Sir Myles her sonne and sir Guy, tooke her vp certainly.</l>
                  <l>Sonnes she said what is your réede, for certis your father is dead.</l>
                  <l>The best réede that I can, is that we slay euary man.</l>
                  <l>Nay said Myles we will not doe so, vnto our father will we go.</l>
                  <l>And bring him good succour, if he be liuing in that stoure.</l>
                  <l>And if that he slaine be, we will reuenged be truly.</l>
                  <l>We will destroy all that cittie, soone they were all readie.</l>
                  <l>Sir Guy destroyed Arum bright, he was heauy and not light.</l>
                  <l>Sir Beuis with his owne hand, wanne it in the holy land.</l>
                  <l>And a noble sword gan he take, that was sir Launcelots Du lake.</l>
                  <l>Miles had Arundell in his hand, that some time ought Rowland.</l>
                  <l>His horse as swift as a swallow, there might no horse him follow.</l>
                  <l>Ships tooke he that tide, and ouer the temes gan they ride.</l>
                  <l>And brought with them to the citie, ten thousand knights frée.</l>
                  <l>They came at a water side, with much ioy and great pride.</l>
                  <l>At Ludgate they gan ariue, and slew all that they found a liue.</l>
                  <l>Certes Lordings I you say, by that sprang the light of the day.</l>
                  <l>Beuis was so wearie in that fight, that vnne this he might sit vpright.</l>
                  <l>There dwelt a lumberd in that towne, a doughtie man of great renowne.</l>
                  <l>And he gathered a great hoast, and rode foorth with great boast.</l>
                  <l>And in his hand a good fauchowne, that was made of stéele browne.</l>
                  <l>And foorth he pricked to sir Beuis, and said, wilt thou aske no trewes.</l>
                  <l>And than anon with his fauchone, he hit Beuis vpon the crowne.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12215:37"/>
                  <l>Beuis for faintnesse laid him low, and leaned vpon his saddle bow.</l>
                  <l>That saw Beuis sonne sir Guy, and gan prick with great enuie.</l>
                  <l>With his sword drawen in his hand, and to the Lumbard sent his sand.</l>
                  <l>So hard on his head he it let, that through helme and basonet.</l>
                  <l>Man and horse in that stound, he smote a sunder to the ground.</l>
                  <l>The point on the pauement glent, that the fire out went.</l>
                  <l>Sir <hi>Beuis</hi> for that stroke lough, and good comfort to him drought.</l>
                  <l>He thanked God omnipotent, that him helpe from heauen sent.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Arundell</hi> for ioy nighed right, and helped <hi>Beuis</hi> for to fight.</l>
                  <l>Sir <hi>Beuis</hi> turned him in that while, and saw his other sonne sir Myle.</l>
                  <l>Came pricking with a great rout, with many armed men him about.</l>
                  <l>He néeded neuer to séeke lech, that sir Miles might ouer rech.</l>
                  <l>Men might heare crownes cracke, when <hi>Beuis</hi> sonnes gan on take.</l>
                  <l>So hard they gan together méefe, that the bloud ran in euery stréete.</l>
                  <l>So many men were dead, that Chepeside was of blood read.</l>
                  <l>For there was slaine I vnderstand, to the number of thirtie thousand.</l>
                  <l>Through the false stewards read, and yet he was the first dead.</l>
                  <l>It is true without lesing, of falsehood commeth no good ending.</l>
                  <l>In euery stréete men might sée, men in great paine to dye.</l>
                  <l>Heads quartered with the thées, shankes cut of by the knées.</l>
                  <l>Hands and armes both cut out, heads with healms trembling about.</l>
                  <l>Dead bodies quartered in thrée, that it was great paine for to sée.</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Beuis</hi> his enemies had destroyed, vnto Putneth he him hied.</l>
                  <l>Iosian was neuer so faine, as when she saw <hi>Beuis</hi> againe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beuis</hi> tooke Iosian full soone, and to soouthhampton came anon.</l>
                  <l>There he thought without faile, to abyde the king battaile.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How the king tooke trwes with Beuis, and wedded his daughter to Miles, and made him Lord of Cornwall, that which longed to sir Brian the kings steward which Beuis slew in the Citie of London.
<pb facs="tcp:12215:37"/>
                  <figure/>
               </head>
               <l>TIdings came to Edgare, of the fighting that was there.</l>
               <l>King Edgare did full rights, send after barons and knights.</l>
               <l>And said by my stewards réed, many of my men were dead.</l>
               <l>I am now an olde man, and Beuis much of warre can.</l>
               <l>He came hether from farre, with great power on me to warre.</l>
               <l>Two sonnes he hath brought, how to agrée I take great thought.</l>
               <l>Miles shall wed my daughter frée, and so our strife asswaged shall bée.</l>
               <l>He shall be Earle of Cornewaile, that was sir Brians without faile,</l>
               <l>All they counsailed them so, a messenger the king sent tho.</l>
               <l>To Beuis of Southhampton, and bad him come to London.</l>
               <l>I will it be ordained so, to make a league betwéene vs two,</l>
               <l>Miles shall wed my daughter frée, and Earle of Cornewall shall he bée,</l>
               <l>Beuis is to London come, the wedding presently begon,</l>
               <l>The Lady to the Church was led, and to sir Miles was she wed,</l>
               <l>The king gaue Miles in spousaile, the earledome of Cornewaile,</l>
               <l>There wes mirth at their spousing, turnament and great iusting,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:12215:38"/>
               <l>At the spousaile in that maner, the king and Beuis sat full néere.</l>
               <l>Now will Beuis home wend, he tooke his leaue of the king so hend.</l>
               <l>And the Lords in that while, and also of his sonne sir Mile.</l>
               <l>He betooke his sonne to sir Sabere, that he should him teach and lere.</l>
               <l>Beuis is gone and sir Guy, Iosion and eke sir Terry.</l>
               <l>Beuis left to them their land, and betooke them to Gods hand.</l>
               <l>Vnto Mambrant he did fare, and seuen yéere he liued there.</l>
               <l>Then waxed Iosian sicke and lay, and Beuis also as I you say.</l>
               <l>Bishops and friers came bliue, Beuis and Iosian for to shriue.</l>
               <l>When Beuis &amp; Iosian the good, were humbled vnto God in mood.</l>
               <l>Each turned to other without bost. and both they yéelded vp the Ghost.</l>
               <l>Much sorow made sir Guy, but it was no boote truely.</l>
               <l>For we must be dead ywis, when that Christes will is.</l>
               <l>Sir Guy to stable went he, Arundell his horse to sée.</l>
               <l>When he came there he found no read, for Arundell was also dead.</l>
               <l>For Guy thought meruaile the loth to say, that all they dyed vpon a day.</l>
               <l>Sir Guy did ordaine and make, for sir Beuis and Iosians sake.</l>
               <l>A place of religion and price, to sing for Iosian and Beuis.</l>
               <l>And tombed them together in feare, king and Quéene as they were.</l>
               <l>Iesu Christ in the Trinitie, on their soules haue mercy.</l>
               <l>Thus endeth Beuis of Southhampton, king and knight of great renowne</l>
               <l>And they that haue heard this talking, Iesu graunt them good ending.</l>
               <l>And bring vs all to heauen blisse, that euer shall last and neuer misse.</l>
               <l>Vnto blesse bring vs hée, that for vs dyed vpon the trée.</l>
            </div>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>❧ <hi>Imprinted at London by Thomas</hi> East, dwelling in Aldersgate streete, at the signe of the black horse.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12215:38"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>